Let's take a
look at surface
integrals in section 14.6.
The motivation for surface
integrals is finding
the mass of a sheet of
material or say
sheet of metal.
It all is based on
the really important
formula that the mass
is the amount of
surface area times
the density.
If we have a density
function which describes
the density at any point
along the surface.
And we can take
the mass to be the
integral of the
density function
over the surface,
where ds here represents
a very small area
along the surface.
So in general, to
find any kind of function,
surface integral,
we have some
function defined on
the surface and we
integrate that function
over the surface.
This has
many important
applications in physics.
If the function measures
the static charge,
we can accumulate
that static charge
across the sheet.
If it measures
the amount of
measures of fluid passing
through a screen,
we can accumulate all of
that fluid to
find the total
amount that's
moved through.
Here's an example
of a triangular
region above a plane,
above a given plane to x
plus y plus z equals three.
And we want, and we have
a density function.
And we want to find
the mass of this
particular, this
particular surface.
First, we need to
parameterize the surface.
And we can start
by parameterizing
the triangular region
below the surface.
So as you moves from 0 to
one and v moves
from 0 to one.
We can describe
any point in
this short triangular
region here with
a x-value view and
a y value of v times
two minus two y2.
And that makes
that assures that
any point u and v in
these intervals
describes a unique point
inside the small triangle.
Now we take that if
we take you far x
value and v times
two minus two y2
for our y value,
put that into the equation
for the plane sulfur z.
To get the z value
in terms of u and v,
We now have a
parameterization for
the triangular
region sitting
above in the plane.
We're going to
find the mass.
So we need to use the
partial derivatives.
So we take the
partial derivative
of r with respect
to u and v,
and we take the derivative
in each component,
and then we find
the cross product
of those two partial
derivatives.
And then the magnitude
of the cross-product,
the density, is given
as a function
of x, y, and z.
So we have to
find the density
in terms of u
and v as well.
So we put our value of,
we put our values for x,
y, and z in terms
of u and v,
found in the previous
slide here, x, y,
and z in terms
of U and V into
the density function
and simplified.
And we now have the density
described in terms
of the variables u
and v. And that allows us
to write the integral
for the mass.
So the mass is the
integral of the
density function over
U and V times
the magnitude of
the cross product
of the derivatives,
and we end up getting
about 12.6 x.
We also want to
measure flux
across the surface.
And for flux, we need
to have a normal
vector along
the surface that tells us
what direction it is
orthogonal to the surface.
The vector that we're
going to use for
the normal vector
is given here.
It's a unit normal vector.
And it's that familiar
cross product
of the partial derivatives
of our parametrization.
So let's take a look at
the same triangular region,
but now we have
a vector field
defined in three-dimensional
space around it.
And we want to
measure the flux
across S. Again,
imagine that this
triangular region
is a screen and
the flux is some
measure of fluid,
a fluid flowing through
it and they are
integral is actually
going to give us a measure
of the amount
of fluid that's
phone, that goes between.
So in the previous
example we found
the cross-product
of the two vectors.
So we have the vector field
when we put in are e, r,
u and v parameterizations
into the unto the f,
which is the vector field.
Now we have the
vector field
described in terms of u and
v. So what is our flux?
Or flux is the integral
over the surface of
the vector field
dot product
with that normal vector.
But since we already
found the normal vector,
we can use the theorem
that allows us to take
the dot product of
the vector field with
the normal vector,
which gives us an
integral from 0 to one.
This function of u and v,
which turns out
to be five-thirds