Welcome to a short video
on an introduction
to vectors.
There's a section
10.2 in our book.
>> Factors can be
thought about simply
as arrows and calculus.
>> We call a vector a
directed line segment.
So that is part
of a line between
two points and it
has a direction,
meaning we want to
think of moving from
a certain initial point
to the terminal point.
Once we have the
initial point
and a terminal point,
the vector has a
length or magnitude,
and the direction is just
the direction that
it's pointing.
Some notation that we use
for vectors is this.
So if we know
the two points
that the vector goes from,
then we can write the
vector has the first,
then the second with
an arrow over the top.
It matters which order
the points appear, right?
That was the vector PQ
is different than
the vector QP.
All vectors that point
in the same direction
and have the same length
are actually the same.
So we can think
of vectors as
arrows that we
simply just move
around wherever
we want to sense.
It doesn't really matter
where the vector
is pointing.
Usually we drop the points
and we just write
the vector as
v or w or u
or something like that with
a little arrow
over the top.
The length or magnitude
of a vector is
written with this double
absolute value notation.
In math, we usually
write vectors as
components with these
angle brackets.
So in R2, or in
two-dimensional space,
a vector is written
as angle bracket
a comma b, another
angle bracket.
>> And that's in the
specific case where
the vector goes from
0 comma 0 to the
point a comma b.
>> We also use this
other notation
for vectors that
you'll see is very
common as either
a row vector
or a column vector.
That is when we're
using vectors in
the context of
matrices usually.
So how do we find
the component
form of vector?
Well, if we're given
two points from p to q,
then we can find
the vector by
subtracting the
initial points
from the terminal points.
>> So in the picture
that you see here,
we have a vector that
goes from a to B.
>> And if you subtract
the initial points from a,
that essentially
translates that vector
down to the origin.
So the vector that
goes from a, B,
C to XYZ is the
same as the vector
that goes from 0002,
x minus a, y minus b,
z minus c. It's best to
think about factors
not as having coordinates,
but each number that's
separated by commas here
just tells you the
value in the x,
y, and z directions
respectively.
So here's an example.
Find the component form of
the vector
whose initial point
is negative three,
negative two, negative one,
and whose terminal point is
negative one to four.
So if we graph the vector
here in
three-dimensional space,
we can just write
the terminal points
negative one to four,
and then subtract
the initial points.
And that gives a
simple calculation.
And it turns out to
be the vector 245
A great thing about vectors
is we can scale them,
meaning that we
can add them
together geometrically,
that Beans stringing
the arrows are chaining
them together and to
seeing where they add up.
So we can see, ie,
the vector u plus
the vector v ends
up over here.
And we call that
total vector u plus
v. And that turns
out to be the
same as v plus u.
This is actually a
property of vectors.
>> Addition takes
place by just
adding up each component.
>> So that's very
convenient. So if you have
the vector with
three components,
U1, U2, U3, and V1, V2, V3.
You just add them
together by adding
each component and then
scaling a vector
is very similar.
When you multiply a
vector times a number,
that number just gets
multiplied on each part.
Not the geometric
interpretation of scaling.
So if you multiply
a vector times two,
that actually
doubles the length.
>> And that means
the length of
each component is
twice the size.
>> Here's
some important
properties of vectors.
Just keep in mind, when
you add vectors together,
you can add them
in any order.
They have the
associative property,
just like real numbers do.
There's a special vector,
sort of the arrow,
the invisible arrow
that's size 0.
And you can add it to
any vector and you just
get the vector back.
When you scale vectors,
you have the nice property
where you can just
multiply times,
multiply first or
scale one at a time.
>> You can
distribute scalars
across two vectors.
>> You can add two scalars
together in a distributed
across the vector.
As we would normally think,
the scalar 0 times
any vector is the 0 vector.
And the magnitude of
a vector behaves this way.
When you scale it,
you can just pull out
the absolute value of
the scalar and you'll
get the same thing.
>> And then
the last property is
pretty important.
>> It says that the
only vector that has
length 0 is the
0 vector itself.
A special kind of vector
is the unit vector.
Unit vector is a
vector of length one.
Given any vector v,
you can always find the
unit vector by just
multiplying times
one over the length.
This just takes
the length of
the vector and scales
it to have length one.
Once you've scaled
vectors have length one,
then you can ask if
they're pointing in
the same direction.
So any two vectors
are parallel,
if they're pointing in
the same direction.
>> And you can check
if they're parallel,
is if you scale
them to length one,
then say if they
are the same,
if they have
the same unit vector
or the opposite.
>> So parallel is
pointing in the
same direction
or opposite directions.
An important thing
about unit vectors
in two dimensions is
every unit vector is
identified with
a specific point on
the unit circle.
So that's a good
way to think about
the direction of vectors
in two dimensional space
is at every point
on the unit circle
is actually the
direction of a vector.
So that means in
component form,
we can write unit vectors
just like we
would in Trig as
the cosine of
the angle comma
the sine of the
angle in threes,
in three-dimensions,
the situation's a little
more complicated.
You have the angle with
the positive x axis
and then you have
the angle with
the positive z axis.
So you can write
the component form
of a unit vector in
three dimensions like this.
And every, every
direction in
three-dimensional space,
every unit vectors
associated
with a point on
the unit sphere.
>> And later on in
the class we'll,
we'll call these
coordinates
spherical coordinates.
>> There's a couple
important vectors
to be aware of.
I and j are the
unit normal vectors
are standard nor stand at
unit vectors in two
dimensional space.
And they're just the
vectors that 0.1
in the x-direction for i,
in one in the
y-direction for j,
and the same in R3.
>> We have the
vectors i, j, and k.
>> These are really
popular vectors
and they're used to
describe any kind of
direction in the,
the normal standard
unit directions,
one in the x direction,
one in the y direction,
and one in the z direction.
So we can always write
factors in these
two different ways.
>> We have the
component form,
which we just learned as
three comma four
comma five.
>> So lets just the
vector that points
three in the x direction
and four in the
y direction,
and five in the
z direction.
>> But we can pull
out those scalars.
>> And what we have
kind of behind
the scenes are these
standard unit vectors.
That means that we
can write the vector
345 is just 3i
plus 4j plus 5K.