Let's take a look at
an overview of section
12.2 on Limits and
Continuity of
multivariable functions.
We have to remind
ourselves of
some properties
of real numbers and
sets of real numbers.
And real numbers.
So we can look at
larger sets into, in
three-dimensional space.
>> In calculus
12, we usually
look at just
intervals, right?
>> Do we have a
closed interval
from 0 to one?
And this is a set of
real numbers that
are between 01,
but also includes
the endpoints.
And when it includes
all of the end points,
we say it's closed.
We're going to call
these endpoints
boundary points
from here on out.
You can also have
half open intervals,
which are neither
open nor closed,
where the interval
contains one of
the endpoints.
And then you have
an open interval
where it doesn't contain
any of the end points.
The open interval, we
call it open because
every point in the interval
is an interior point,
which sort of means
it's on the inside.
So you want to, we want
to extend these ideas
to sets in two-dimensional
space, or an R2.
For looking at sets
in two dimensions,
we want to be able to
consider the open disk.
That's a very important
set in two dimensions,
which is just the circle,
the inside of a circle
of radius one,
in this case,
bore of any radius,
we have closed sets.
And closed sets
are sets that
contain the
entire boundary.
So every point that's on
the edge is
contained inside
the set that are
open sets which do not
contain the boundary.
And in fact,
every point and
an open set is an
interior point,
which means that it's
completely surrounded
by other points in the set.
And then there
are sets that are
neither open nor closed.
So when we're talking about
functions of two or
three variables,
the language of open
and closed sets is
very useful in
the way that open
and closed intervals
where in calculus one.
Also we want to be
familiar with
the idea being
bounded and
unbounded as a set.
So here we defined
bounded to mean
that the set can
be contained in
some giant desk.
So in the example
on the left here,
we have our set
and there's,
there exists at least one
giant disk that
contains it.
So that means that site is
bounded on the right,
we have this
sort of infinite
sector that goes forever.
>> There is no disc
that can contain that,
that area right there.
>> So that's an
unbounded set.
>> So here's an example.
>> Determine the domain of
the function one
over x minus y,
whether it's closed,
open, or neither.
Well, the domain or
the set of points where
the function is defined.
In this case, the only
thing that can go
bad is if the
denominator is 0.
So the domain is
the set of points
where x minus y is not 0.
And that's the set
of points where
y is not equal to x.
So that's everything except
for the line y equal to x.
This set is open because
if you take any
point in the set,
you are completely
surrounded
by other points in the set.
That means that
every point is
an interior point,
the sets unbounded,
because we can kind of
see that any large disk
that we try is not
going to contain
the entire set.
So the domain here is
open and unbounded.
We also wanna
be able to talk
about the limit of
a function of two
or three variables.
The way we talk about
a limit is very
similar to calculus one.
But when we approach a
point in the domain,
now we are approaching
from other points
in the domain.
And it's not just from
left or the right,
or above or below, but
approaching in any way.
But the definition
of the limit is very
similar to the definition
of a limit from
calculus one.
We say that the
function f approaches
owl as we approach
the point x-naught,
y-naught here, if for
any given epsilon,
tiny, tiny small
number that you may
choose epsilon that we
can find a disk
small enough so that
every point
within the disk,
if we evaluate
the function,
its difference
from the limit
is less than epsilon.
>> So do not be Technical.
>> Where we can
say is that as
we approach the point,
the functions values
approach the limit l,
we have properties
of limits
just as we did
in calculus one.
The important thing here
is all of these
properties are very
nice and we take
advantage of
them at the limit
of the sums,
the sum of the
limits that we
can pull constants
outside of the limits.
And we can take the limit
of a multiplication,
and that's just
the multiplication
of the limits and so on.
But the thing to
keep in mind is that
these properties
only only work,
especially properties like
number 4567 down here,
if the separate limits
exist to themselves,
so you can create
situations
where maybe the
product limit exists.
So maybe number five,
you can multiply
two functions,
then the limit exists,
but the functions
themselves,
the limit may not exist.
In that case,
number five maybe
broken and maybe you
will not even
get the product.
This is a reminder
that in calculus one,
calculus two, when
you wanted to
take limits of functions,
we can determine
if the limit
existed by approaching
from the right,
which we had a
little plus, and
approaching from the
left a little minus.
And if we got
the same value
as we approached from
the right and the left,
than that means
the limit exists.
We can't do that in
two dimensional space
because we can approach
from infinitely
many directions.
So we want to be able
to look at limits of
functions and determine
if they exist or not.
And if they exist,
how can we find them?
So first, we'll look
at an example to
show that a limit
does not exist.
The limit has to
exist if it's
the same as we approach
from any direction.
So an easy way
to get started
here is to try
approaching from
some simple directions and
then see if we're
getting the same limit.
So in this case,
we're approaching
the 0 comma 0.
And some easy directions
to try would be maybe
from the right
or from above.
>> If we approach
from the right,
that means the y
value is always
0 and x is a
positive number.
>> And if we put
those values into
the function,
we see we've kind of gotten
rid of the y-value.
So we're just
finding the limit
of a function of a
single variable.
>> Again, we see that
we're just taking
the limit of 0 over X
squared equals to 0.
>> So the limit of
this function as we
approach from
the right is 0.
And similarly, if we
approach from above,
in that case,
the x value is 0, and
we're taking the
limit of 0 over
y squared equals to 0.
And because we could
have just put the
limit as x goes to 0,
even from the
left or below.
>> Because of these
squared terms,
we also would
have gotten 0.
>> So for this
particular function,
if we approach from
the left to
right, we get 0.
And if we approach
from the top
or the bottom, we get 0.
>> But the problem
is saying that the
limit doesn't exist.
>> Although we seem
to have some evidence
that the limit does
exist and it is 0.
But just because
it's approaching
0 from these
directions doesn't
mean the limit 0
because it can approach
from where it has to be
0 as we approach
from any direction.
So the next thing
to try is to
approach along an
arbitrary line.
So let's say we want to
approaches 0 comma
0 along a line
with slope m. While
we know a line that
goes through 0 comma 0 with
slope m is y equals to m x.
So we can do is
parameterize
that line with
a vector valued
function with a t for x.
And then the y value
would be M times t.
>> We can approach 0
comma 0 as t goes to 0.
>> And you can see in
these expressions here,
the limit of the
function along
the line is we
approach our x and
our y values with t
and M t that are
parameterizations.
And then the
t's cancel out.
And we can see
that the limit of
the function as
we approach along
a line with slope m
is three m over m
squared plus one.
So it actually depends
on the slope of the line.
So for slope,
two different slopes give
us two different limits.
So therefore, the
limit cannot exist.
Now let's look
at an example
where the limit does exist,
and we need to prove it.
To get started with these,
it helps to try some
values x and y.
>> Maybe is layer 0 comma
0 with a computer
or a calculator?
>> See what you get
and see if there's
evidence that what
the limit might be.
Here I graphed the function
with the 3D calculator.
And this is what the
function looks like.
And we're looking at
the point right over
here at 0 comma 0.
So it seems that if
a limit does exist,
the limits probably 0
So we need to prove that
the limit is indeed
0 using the epsilon
definition.
So given a small
number epsilon,
we need to produce a delta.
So that numbers within
the disk of radius delta,
which satisfies
square root of
x squared plus y squared
will imply that anytime
we have those x comma wise,
if we put them
into the function,
that number's distance from
0 will be less
than epsilon.
So these take practice
and we can go through
some examples.
And it's sort of
an advanced
technical problem,
but it's best to
work backwards.
And when you do that,
we see in this example
that there was
a judicious
choice for delta,
which was the square root
of epsilon over five.
And the proof is
in the putting it,
let's see if it works.
So if you take the
absolute value of
the function we get here,
and we can separate
it like this,
which helps us
determine which are
the parts are, are growing,
in which the parts
are small, we can,
all we're trying to
do is prove that this
is less than epsilon.
And we're going
to use the fact
that the square root
of x squared plus y
squared is less than delta.
>> But here, y
squared over x squared
plus y squared,
that part is less
than or equal
to one, right?
>> Because the bottom
here is always going to be
greater than the top.
So that that
expression is now less
than the absolute value
of five x squared.
But since we have x
squared plus y
squared is less than
delta squared because
of our assumption here.
>> That means x squared
is less than all of that.
>> So we have x squared
being less than
delta squared.
And then we can replace
delta squared with
epsilon over five,
because that was our
choice for delta.
And we can see that
that is all epsilon.
So when you string
these equalities and
inequalities together,
what we've
concluded is that
0 arc candidate
for a limit,
the distance from f is
less than epsilon for
that given delta.
Therefore, this limit
exists and is equal to 0.
We can also talk about
continuity of a function.
The continuity,
the continuity of
a function is defined
similar to calculus one.
Its continuous
if it's a limit
exists and it's equal
to the value at that point.
So that's what
it means to be
continuous at a point.
And it's continuous
on an entire set.
If it's continuous at every
point in that whole set.
The properties of
continuous functions are
also analogous
to calculus one.
And this is a relief
because that means that we
don't have to remember
anything new here.
That when you have
continuous functions,
if you add them
together, you
also get a
continuous function.
You multiply them
times a constant,
you also get a
continuous function.
So these are very
useful in actually
proving that a function
is continuous.
If we can view
that function
as simpler pieces of
continuous function,
we want to show that
a function might
be continuous.
>> This is asking if
it's continuous at 0,
if it's continuous at 00,
that must mean the
limit must exist.
>> The limit of
the function
as x goes to 0 must
exist and be equal
to 0 comma 0.
So we can check
the 0 comma 0 if
we put it in,
that gives us the top were
in the top case,
and that's one.
And that's the same
as the limit as,
as, as x comma y
approaches 0 comma 0.
>> The way we can do that
is this little trick.
>> And this is kind
of reminiscent
of some limit tricks
from calculus.
One, This is separating
the expression in terms
of the x's and y's.
And since we're,
we're going to use
that previous theorem
that says that
the limit of a product
is the product
of the limits.
And of course,
the limit here on
the right is just one.
The cosine is
continuous at 0,
so the limit is one,
the same as what
we got if we
put in the 0 comma 0.
So indeed it is
continuous at 00.
>> You can do a similar
kind of analysis
to show that it's actually
continuous everywhere
because of these limits
holding for functions
of three variables.
>> Everything we
just discussed for
a function of two
variables is also true,
except that we have
these additional terms
with the z values in them.