Let's take a look at
arc length and curvature.
>> This is an
overview of Section
11.51 and motivation.
When we want to describe
the position of an
object around a curve,
we can do it
with a different
parameterizations.
So on the pictures
on the bottom left,
we have one
parameterization
that shows that at
time equals to 0,
where at this
red point, time
equals to one here.
At time equals to two here.
Looking at the points as
t moves gives
us some kind of
indication of the speed
that the position
changes along the curve.
On the curve on the right,
S denotes arc length.
So here, when S is 0,
if you move one distance
along the curve,
you get S equal to one.
We move one more distance
along the curve,
we get S equal to two.
So the parametrization
on the left gives us
a parameterization
in terms at a time.
Unit t, the premises
realization on
the right because
of privatization.
In terms of the arc length,
the distance S. To
understand arc length,
let's start with
a curve and
remember that we
can have different
parameterizations.
The example here is
if you have the curve
y equals x squared,
which is the
well-known parabola.
We can parameterize
that curve with
a position vector
t comma t squared.
Or we could do it with
this vector here,
two t for t squared.
The difference is, is
that the second one,
an object will move much
faster compared
to the first.
But at the end of the day,
they're tracing
the same curve,
y equals x squared.
When we're finding
arc length,
we can actually start
with any parameterization.
So you're doing
calculations is probably
a good idea to start with
the simplest one possible.
So then the arc length
of the curve along
the interval 0 to t is
given by the
following expression.
It's the integral from 0 to
t of the magnitude of the
derivative. So
here's an example.
Here's a position
vector along a curve.
Let's find the
parameterization
with respect to
the arc length
S. First we take
its derivative.
Then the arc length is
the integral from 0 to
t of the magnitude
of r prime.
There's a small typo
here, should be R prime.
And that's the square
root of this sum of
the squares of
the components.
And so we end up getting
that the arc length
S is equal to five
t. We can use
the relationship
between S and
T to solve for t and then
substitute that back in to
the original
parametrization to
get the permutations
in terms of s.
So here, if we solve for t,
we get S over five.
And if you put S
O S divided by
five in for t into the
original function,
we get this new
parameterization
in terms of the arc length
s. And this
parameterization
has a number of
benefits as we'll see.
So let's investigate this
arc length parameter
a little bit.
If we take the derivative
of both sides of
the definition of
the arc length,
that gives us this.
This tells us that
the rate at which
the arc length changes
is simply the magnitude
of the derivative.
Well, this is what
we called speed.
So the derivative of,
the derivative of
the arc length
with respect to
time is the speed.
If we apply the chain rule
and we take the
derivative of
the position vector
function with respect to
time, we get the following.
And then you can solve for
the derivative of
the curve with
respect to s,
And that gives us the
unit tangent vector.
So the arc length
is actually the
parameterization,
which is the one
that always moves at
a constant velocity of one.
Curvature is the
measure of how
much a curve bends.
It's actually a
measure of how much
the unit tangent
vector is turning.
Once you've
parameterised your
curve with respect
to the arc length
parameter.
We can find the
curvature by taking
the magnitude of
the derivative
of the unit tangent vector.
It turns out in certain
situations when
the curve is described
in different ways,
if flicker in number
one, if the curve is
described just y as
a function of x,
you can easily find
the curvature with
this formula.
If you're just curve
is described with
our parameterization and
are in two-dimensional
space.
You can find it with
number two here.
And then if it's defined
by a general vector
valued function,
you can use number three.
These three formulas just
involve some, some algebra.
So here's an example.
Find the curvature
of a circle with
radius r given by this.
This is a circle
spinning
counterclockwise with
radius r. Since the curve
is given to us in this
form, x of t, y of t.
>> We can use option two in
the previous slide
in our problem,
X is equal to r cosine t,
y is equal to r sine t.
>> So you can find
its derivatives
and squares and
then plug it with
all of that into
the formula for
the curvature.
>> And when you
plug that all,
then you end up
getting that
the curvature
is one over r.
>> So unsurprisingly,
the curvature
of a circle of
radius r is inversely
proportional to the
radius of the circle.
So the bigger the
circle gets smaller,
the curvature
is going to be,
the smaller the radius,
the larger the curvature
is going to be.