Hi, class.
>> Let's take a look at
an overview of Section
13.1 on iterated
integrals and area.
This is the introduction of
integrals of functions
of more than one.
>> Brave to motivate
what's going on here.
>> If we have a function f
of x and y and its
partial derivative
with respect to X.
>> How do we get the
function f back?
>> Well, in calculus one,
if we were just
talking about
a function of a
single variable,
you would take its
antiderivative and
you would have
the function f back plus
some constant
integration here.
We can integrate
the derivative
with respect to
x, with respect to x.
And then we do
get the function
back plus some
constant integration.
But since we
integrated with
respect to x here,
the constant of integration
might be any function of y.
And that makes sense
if we were to look at
both sides of this
equation here and
take the derivative
with respect to x.
If we take the
derivative respect to
x of the right
hand side here,
we get the derivative
of f with respect to x.
And then the
derivative respect
to x of a function of
y would just be 0.
So let's integrate the
following function.
Since we're integrating
with respect to x,
the limits of integration
can be with respect to
any other variable.
So you find the
anti-derivative
with respect to x,
thinking of y
as a constant,
and apply the
fundamental theorem of
calculus as we usually
would put again,
the values of
two i and one is
the limits of integration,
taking the difference.
Now this is another common
situation where
we're trying to
find the integral of a
function of x and y,
first with respect
to y, then
with respect to x.
This is called an
iterated integral.
Sometimes it's
understood that you're
taking and take the
derivative with
respect to y first,
Thus the d y appearing
before the dx.
And will you just
drop the parentheses?
So we would just do this
one step at a time.
So working on the
inside integral,
you would take the
antiderivative
of this time with
respect to y and
evaluate at the limits of
integration here at X
and X and one and take
the difference,
simplify a bit.
And then what you have
is just a function of x,
and that's just a normal
Calc Two type integral.
>> What does the 89 over
eight even mean though?
>> So we are given this
original expression,
which is a double integral.
And we got the answer
which is just a number.
>> So we're going to see
that this function
of two variables,
x and y, that we're given
its graph writers in
three-dimensional space.
>> And its graph
is a surface
that is above and
below the XY plane.
>> And the double
integral here is
actually finding
the volume underneath
the graph of
that function
between bounded
between the graph of
the function in
the x, y plane.
So that's what this number
89 over eight refers to.
>> So if we were to
sketch the region of
integration for
this example, and
what does that mean?
>> That means finding
the region in
the domain of the function
for which we're
finding the integral.
So here for any fixed x
looking on the
outside between 12.
So for any x between 12,
we are going to
integrate a y from
one up to y equals to x.
>> So this
particular integral
is integrating over
the region R in
the picture here.
>> And it's doing
it by integrating
vertical strips one
acts at a time and
then accumulating all of
those vertical strips
to get the volume.
>> Sometimes once we know
the region on which
we're integrating over,
it's common to write
the two integral signs with
just the region
name underneath it.
Now this expression here
is the double integral of
the function over
that region.
But to actually find
it and calculate it,
we need to write it as an
iterated integral
as it was given.
>> So a lot of
problems start
by providing an integral
that looks like this.
>> And we have
to use the limits
of integration,
find the sort of nature
and character of
the region in order to
write it as an
iterated integral.
Here, DA is sort of
referring to
either dx or dy y.
So it's convenient
to be able to,
to integrate functions of
two variables that are
bounded by two functions
on the top and the bottom.
>> And we can integrate
them the way that we
would normally want to.
>> One easy application for
these double
integrals is just
finding areas in the plane.
>> So if we have an area
bounded between the,
this region R here,
but bounded between
these red lines and these
two blue functions.
How could we find
the volume of our,
well, you could do
this in a calculus
to sense, right?
>> You could
just accumulate
the area in between.
>> But one, right?
Now we want to
think about it
as this area is
the same thing
as the volume
of this area with
a height of one.
>> And that allows
us to write
it as a double integral.
>> So the volume
of this region is
the area of each of
these vertical strips
between g2 and g1.
>> So this is G2 minus g1.
And we can write it as
this integral here.
So this is a common way of
finding areas in the plane.
And this is the
contents of theorem
three to 13.1.1
in our text.
>> Another really
common example
with iterated integrals.
>> And this we'll see
later that many integrals,
perhaps we can't
do it because
the function here has
no anti-derivative.
But if we change
the order of
integration or do a
change of coordinates
>> Maybe the new
function that we end
up with does have
an anti-derivative.
>> So changing the
order of integration
given an integral is
a common thing to do,
but the meat of the
matter really has to
do with understanding of
the region that we're
integrating over.
And that allows us to
change the limits of
integration to make sure
that we're integrating
over the same region.
>> So let's take a look
at this example here.
>> The first thing to
do is to understand
the region that we're
integrating over here.
We're integrating from y,
going from 0 to four,
but where x goes
between these two
functions of y,
so this is this
picture here.
So y goes between 04,
x is going to go between
y plus four over two,
which is this line
2x y squared over
four, which is here.
So the region that
we're integrating over
here is this
purple region R.
>> And we're integrating it
by accumulating the
horizontal strips, right?
>> For if, for each
y we get region,
we get x going
between these two
functions of y.
And then the
integral accumulates
those horizontal strips.
And then finally,
we accumulate that,
we accumulate those
horizontal strips
by integrating
with respect to y.
>> So how do we change
it to be an integral?
>> First with respect to y,
then with respect to X.
>> Well now we have to
sort of cut the volume.
>> So the, think about it.
The graph is
relating sitting
above this picture
of the region.
So we're really
finding a volume and
risk finding that
volume by cutting it,
by cutting its
cross sections
in a certain,
certain directions.
So now we want to cut
those cross sections
vertically up and down.
>> But if we do that,
we see that our region
are the nature of
its bounds actually changes
here at x equal to two.
>> Because when
x is equal to,
when x is between 02,
we can see the two
functions y equals to
0 and this line here,
which is y equals
two to x when
you solve for y
in this equation.
So it's going to bound,
the bounds are
going to be between
y equals 0 and
y equals two to x in
this first region, R1.
>> And then the bounds
are going to be
between here.
>> When you
solve for y, you
get y equals 2x,
2x minus four.
So the bounds
are going to be
between equals to
two root x and y equals
2x minus four
in this region.
>> But it's important
that we see this as
two separate pieces
because the limits
of integration
are going to be
different on
these two pieces.
>> So we have to
actually split up the
integral into the sum of
two integrals in order to
write the integral
in terms of dy, dx.
>> Okay?
>> So we take the
original integral,
we write it as the sum of
the integrals of
the same function.
We're just integrating
the function
one here because
we're finding
the area over
these two regions.
But over these two regions,
we need to find these
two new boundaries.
And that allows
us to rewrite
the limits of integration.
Now with respect to
the dy by dx integral,
notice how we can't just
swap roles x and y.
That's a very
common mistake.
If these problems, we
can't just switches,
switch x and y's and
expect to be integrating
over the exact same region.
We really do have to draw
the region and think about
how the limits of
integration are going
to describe that region.
But now we're given
two iterated
integral separately.
So we can use
our normal techniques of
integration to find
these integrals.