Let's take a look at
surface area and
Section 13.5.
We'll start by estimating
a small little piece of
surface area by subdividing
the region underneath
the function
of two variables
and then finding
the area of
the associated
small rectangle
in the surface.
>> So we have a
small rectangle
in the domain of
the function.
>> And we see we have
these two vectors
that point in you in
the direction of the
positive x direction
and v in the positive
y direction.
And if we could find
those two vectors,
we could estimate the area
of that small rectangle
with the magnitude of
the cross-product of
those two vectors.
So first we want to
find those two vectors.
Well, u is in
the direction of
the positive x-axis
and it's direct.
Its length in the
positive x direction
is delta x i.
In this case envies
length in the y
direction is delta y i.
And the vector u changes
with respect to the,
how the function is
changing in the
X direction.
And that's the derivative
with respect x.
And the function in the
vector v changes in
the z direction as
f changes in the
y direction.
And that's the derivative
of f with respect to y.
>> So this actually
tells us what
the vectors u
and v must be.
>> So now we can
write our derivation.
>> The small piece
of surface area here
is approximated
by the area of
the rectangle
formed by u and v.
>> But the area of
the rectangle
formed by U and V
is the magnitude of
the cross-product of
those two vectors.
>> But the two vectors
are as given here.
And if we find the
cross product,
we get this nice formula
with the square root of one
plus the sum of
the squares of the
partial derivatives.
>> So the total
surface area
is actually approximated by
the sum over all of
these small little squares,
small little rectangles of
these approximations
that we found above.
>> So the key
here is to let
the small rectangles gets
smaller and smaller
and smaller.
And if we let the
limit go to 0,
we get that a small
change in surface area is
approximated by
this differential
here with a small
change in the area.
>> And that allows
us to define an
integral to tell us
what the surface areas.
>> So let's take a look at
the surface of a sphere.
We can find the surface
of a sphere by just looking
at the top half of
it and then
we'll double it.
But the equation for the
top half of a sphere
of radius a is given
with this function,
we can find its
partial derivatives.
>> So then the surface area
by integral formula
is just two times
the integral,
the double integral
over the region R.
>> In this case,
the region R is
the disk of radius
a centered at 00.
>> And if we substitute
in our partial derivatives,
we get the
following integral.
Now we just covered
integration of
polar coordinates,
and we should
see that that's
a good thing to use
here because we have
x squared plus y squared,
which we know is r-squared.
>> And hopefully
that will give us
a simpler expression to
write as an
iterated integral.
>> And indeed we do so.
>> If we write x and y,
x is r cosine theta,
y is r sine theta.
>> And make our
substitutions,
we get the
following integral,
which doesn't look nicer,
but it does simplify down.
Now here we'll
notice that we do
have an improper integrals.
>> So we do have to
worry about the limit
as R approaches a,
because then the
bottom here is 0.
But if we're careful
with the limits and we,
and we do our substitution
where u is a squared
minus r squared.
>> We end up with a
simpler integral here.
>> And we get that
the surface area of
the sphere is four
pi a squared,
which is what we knew
it was from earlier.
>> Geometry