Let's look at the
volume between
surfaces and triple
integration.
>> This is section 13.6.
If we have two functions of
two variables
over a region R,
then we can find the volume
of the space between
them by just taking the
double integral of
their difference.
Essentially this is
just saying that the,
you take the
larger volume of f
between surface
and they XY axis,
subtract the volume from
the service of g to the x,
y axis, and then
you get the volume
in-between.
>> Here we have an
example where we
want to find the volume of
the region bounded
between two planes
and the coordinate axes
x equal to 0 and
y equal to 0.
>> First, we want to
figure out what is
the region of integration
that we're
integrating over.
>> So what is the area in
the XY plane for
which we want to
find the integral.
>> This involves
finding where
these two planes intersect.
So defined where
the two points
intersect, you set the,
their equations
that must be
true equal to each
other simplify.
And we see that the
line 2x plus y equal to
four defines that
region where
they intersect.
So therefore, our
region of integration
then is x being
bounded between
02 and y being
04 minus 2x.
We can draw picture
of this region.
>> And here we'll
integrate DY DX.
>> So for any x, fixed x
between 02 will integrate
y from 0 to the
function four minus 2x.
>> That allows us
to write the double
integral has an
iterated integral.
And then we evaluate that
integrated integral,
integral normally.
And we see that
the answer is 16.
>> So 16 R is the number of
cubic units bounded between
these two planes in
this particular region.
>> We can also view
the same example,
the same volume as a
triple, triple integral.
>> So a triple
integral is the
integral over a region,
planar region R,
but over a
three-dimensional region,
which we'll call d. And the
triple integral can be
written as an
iterated integral.
>> In this case,
where the last
integral is just
the same expression
that we had before,
where we were looking
at the, the distance,
the vertical distance,
you might say
the z distance between
the top plane and
the bottom plane.
>> So instead of
just subtracting
those two functions,
we see that's
just a result of
the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
If we integrate with those
as the limit of
integration,
limits of integration d z.
>> We can find a
triple integrals by
Looking at the
iterated integrals.
>> If our region happens to
be bounded by functions,
the definition of the
triple integral and how it
works comes down to
the same process as
defining the
double integral,
where there were looking at
smaller and
smaller rectangles
in the region
of integration.
And here we're looking at
smaller and smaller cubes
and the region
of integration.
Then we take the limit as
those cubes get smaller
and smaller and smaller.
>> And that's how we
define the triple integral.
>> Now here's a
region bounded by
a plane and the,
and the coordinate axes.
>> So we want to
determine this volume.
And because now that
we're looking at triple
integrals with a DX,
DY, DZ, there's actually
six different ways
we can do it.
>> D z, d y, dx,
dy dx, dy Weiss, and so on.
So the thing is, is
each choice on how you
decide to write the
integral should give
us the correct answer.
>> But it may differ
in terms of how the
integral gets
calculated because
of the limits of
integration might
be different.
>> So let's first look
at the case where
we integrated with
respect to z first.
>> That means
that we're going
to first look at
the portion of our
region in the xy axis.
And we can see here that's
bounded by the
line y equals
2x minus six minus 2x.
And we can get
that by letting z
equals to 0 in
the equation of
the plane here.
>> And so that's our region
R that we would normally
integrate over.
But now we want
to integrate z,
right when z is 0 to
the top of this region,
but the top of
the regions bounded
by the plane.
So we're going
to integrate DZ
from 0 to the plane.
>> And then we'll
integrate y
from 0 to six minus 2x.
>> Since that's
the function of X,
that's the boundary
of the region.
>> And then we'll
integrate x
finally from 0 to three.
>> Now if we change,
we leave DZ to be first.
So we're still
integrating from
the bottom here
and on the x,
y axis to the top
of the plane.
>> But now we're going to
change the
direction in which
we integrate with
respect to x and then y.
So notice that
if we this line
here that denotes
the boundary of
the bottom region,
if we were to
solve for x would
be three minus 1.5 y.
So there we would integrate
x from 0 to three
minus 1.5 Y.
And then finally integrate
y from 0 to six,
which shows in these
limits of integration.
>> Now let's integrate
with respect
to x first.
>> So then the base of our
integral is now
in the YZ axis.
>> So we're going
to integrate from x
equals to 0 to the plane.
>> But the plane, if
you were to solve for x
here is three minus
1.5 y minus three z.
>> Then we integrate
with respect to y.
>> If we solve for y here,
we get six minus three. Z
Which gives us this
boundary. And finally,
x from 0 to two,
I'm sorry, z from 0 to two.
And again, we can
switch the DZ, DY.
And all that's different
is we will now write
this boundary of the region
as two minus 1 third Y.
>> And now we
finally integrate
x, I'm sorry, and
to integrate,
integrate y from
0 to six K.
>> And then
finally we look at
the reading the integrals
with respect to y first.
>> So now we have the
base and the z-axis.
We integrate y
from its base,
from 0 to the plane.
And if you solve
for y here,
you get six minus
2x minus three z.
Then we integrate
with respect to z.
And we can see that
this gives us
the boundary of
two minus two
thirds x and then,
and then finally x
from 0 to three.
And then similarly,
if we change
the dx and DZ again,
and I'll throw in all
six of these integrals.
The answer is 66 is
what we get for the volume.
Now, which one should
we choose if all
through all six of
these integrals give
us the same answer.
Six, the answer
typically is the
one with the easiest
calculations to do.
And in this case,
it kinda comes down to
maybe less fractions here.
And number 56, we
get somewhat of
a nicer expression to
work with immediately.
>> Here's another example.
>> We want to find
the volume of
the region d shown here,
which is bounded above by
the plane z equals
to minus y,
and bounded below by the x,
y axis and the
cylinder x squared plus
y squared equal to one.
So if we set up the triple
integral with respect to
z first than the base
is going to be in
the x, y axis.
And we see the base here
as the hemisphere in
the negative y hemisphere
of a circle of radius
one and the negative
y direction.
>> So that's going to
set up an interval,
an integral with,
with respect to
d z d by dx.
So we can set up
the integral.
And we're first
gonna integrate d
z from 0 to negative Y.
>> Again.
>> Again, if we take
an arbitrary point
here and then we
integrate from z equals
to 0 to the top.
>> The top is bounded
by this plane.
>> So that's
where we get the
0 to negative y.
>> And then d y is gonna go
from negative root one
minus x squared to 0.
>> Well, that's
going to be here
on the edge of the circle.
>> X squared plus y
squared equal to one.
If you were to solve for,
solve for y, and
then we were on
the negative Y.
So we want the negative
square root of
one minus x squared
all the way to 0.
So that sets up the
second integral.
Then finally, X
is going to be
integrating from
negative one to one.
Now this is just an
iterated integral where we
integrate the inside
from the inside out.
So here the answer
is two-thirds.
>> An important property
of triple integral
integrals,
similar to double
is that we might be
trying to do triple,
triple integral over
a spacial region.
That's quite complicated,
or it's just
not possible to
write a simple iterated
integral over that region,
maybe because
the boundaries
aren't described by
a single function.
>> Well, what we
can do is take
that region and
divide it cleverly into
pieces that can be
written easily.
And then we can
find the overall
integral as the sum
of the easier pieces.
>> We can write triple
integrals bounded
by functions with the
following formula.
>> This is just the,
the general case of what we
saw in our
examples earlier.
>> And then the definition
of the triple integral of
a function is
similarly defined.
It's the limit of these
small little pieces,
a volume times the function
and add it all
up to approximate
the integral.
>> But then we
take the limit as
those small pieces
of volume go to 0.
So an immediate application
that we see with a triple
integral over
of a function of
three variables.
>> Here is thinking about
the function being
the density function.
>> Because if we have
a spatial region D,
and we have a density
function on that region.
And then integrating
that with
respect to the area
is going to give
us the mass.
Once we have a way
to find the mass,
then we can find the center
of mass of the region.
>> And indeed That's
what we have here.
>> We can find
that mass over a
bounded region of
space with a
density function
with the triple integral,
we can find the moments
with respect to the YZ,
X Z and X, Y plane.
Remember, these
moments are just,
they're sort of
numerators of
the weighted average right,
in each direction.
And correspondingly, this
one in the x direction,
this one in the
y direction,
z direction.
So that, and then
we divide by
the overall mass and we
get the center of
mass of the object.