Let's take a look at
the cross product.
This is an overview
of section 10.4.
The cross-product
is an operation
between two vectors
in three-dimensional space.
You should note
that we can't
take the cross product of
two vectors in
two dimensional
space that doesn't exist.
So the way that you find
the cross product of
two vectors is with
this somewhat complicated
formula here.
So one way to find the
cross product is just to
memorize this formula or
put it into a computer.
But there is actually
a handy procedure
for calculating
the cross-product
that involves the
same procedure as
finding the determinant
of a matrix.
So let's take
a short detour
into matrices and
determinants.
>> A matrix is just an,
a rectangular
array of values,
array of numbers.
>> And the determinant
of a matrix is a way
of kind of measuring how
large the matrix
size in some way.
Now, in order to
take the determinant
of a three-by-three matrix,
we need to know
how to take the
determinant a two by two.
And the determinant
of a 2-by-2 matrix
is you multiply across
the diagonal AD and then
subtract the
off-diagonal BC.
Now for the determinant
of a three-by-three matrix,
the way that the
book describes
is this diagonal trick,
which is nice and
it works great
for three by
three matrices.
>> But what I'm
showing you here is
the method for
co-factor expansion,
which is actually a way to
calculate determinants
of any size.
>> Add some more relatable
to linear algebra.
Now that determined
the three by three matrix,
you typically do this.
You pick a row or a
column to expand across.
In this case, we're
going to go a, B, and C.
>> So first we
start with a,
and we see that a is here.
>> And we cross out the row
and the column where a is,
and then the numbers that
are left in the matrix,
we take the
determinant of that.
So we take a times
the determinant of the
sub-matrix E F H I.
Now we go over to B and we
alternate sign,
so it's minus.
We cross out the row and
the column where there's B.
And then we take
the determinant
of the matrix.
That's laughed
when we cross
those out, df, GI.
>> And then finally C.
>> Cross out the
row and column and
take the determinant of
the matrix that's left.
Then finally, we just
have the numbers a, b,
and c multiplied times
determiner of
2-by-2 matrices,
which we can find that
the formula above.
And that's how we can get
the determinant of a
three-by-three matrix.
It seems very complicated,
but you just
hold off and see
how much easier it is
once we have numbers.
So here's an example here.
Here we're going to take
the determinant of a
three-by-three matrix.
Two, negative 3120,
negative 11 for five.
So we start with the
matrix and we want to do
co-factor expansion
along the
top two, negative 31.
So you cross
out the row and
column with the
two and we see
of the following matrix 0,
negative 14 or five,
same with their negative
three and the same
with the one.
And we alternate signs.
So it's a positive two,
it's a minus negative
three and plus one.
>> And then here
we keep the two.
>> And the negative
three and the one
here I combined minus
negative three
is plus three.
And then we take
the determinant
of this 2-by-2 matrix,
0 times five
minus four times
negative one and so on.
So at this point, we are
just multiplying and
subtracting numbers
and we get our value of 49.
So the determinant of
this matrix is 49.
So now we will
learn to do is
find the cross product
of two vectors.
So as advertised,
the cross product
of two vectors is
found with this
determinant formula.
So what you do is you
put the vectors i,
j, and k on the top.
And then you put
your first vector u,
its coordinates
along the first row,
the second row, and then
the, the third row.
And so once you
have this matrix,
we want to take the
determinant with
this same method that
we already did, i, j,
and k. So we
expand it along
the top I times
the determinant of
the 2-by-2 sub-matrix
and then minus
j times the determinant
of its sub matrix
and so on.
And what you end
up getting is
four i minus 11 j
plus eight k. And we
can write that in our
bracket form like this.
So the cross product
of the vectors 20,
negative 1145 is the
vector for negative 118.
>> Ok?
>> So since this is a
technical procedure,
numbers are happen
to be nice here.
>> We were able to
calculate it fairly easily.
>> What if the
numbers are not nice?
Or you need to calculate
a whole bunch of
cross-products and you want
to use a computer.
>> So what I have here
is a Jupyter Notebooks,
which is a web-based way
of using Python code.
>> And I have several
examples of this,
and I'll be using
a throw the class,
so please feel free
to ask questions about it.
So if we want to find
the cross product with
Python and the
package Numpy.
You can, you can run
a piece of code like this.
We import the
NumPy package.
The vector u, I'm
putting in as to 0,
negative one, the vector V,
and putting in as 145.
And then we can simply run
the cross method
on the bag.
And the vectors u and v to
find with W is printed out.
>> And we see
that for negative
118 is the answer.
>> The nice thing
about this is
that no matter what
the numbers are,
you can just put
them in here.
Hit Enter, bam,
and then you
have your crossbar quickly.
And there's all,
you can do many,
many things with
this software
and it's good if you,
even if you're
not using this,
it's good to have some kind
of computer software that
you're using to help
you with the calculations
after you've done
it by hand to
verify that they're correct
and to sort of learn
how to do this
because eventually
you'll be
using some kind of
calculator
calculating software.
If you're gonna do
mass calculations
like cross product or
dot product and
things like that.
>> Okay, so what are the
properties of the
cross product?
>> Here we have,
we see that the
cross-product of
u cross v is not the
same as E cross you.
It's actually the
negative of it.
This is called antique
communitivity.
And it's just
important to remember
that cross-product
isn't like multiplication
in the sense
that two times three
is three times two.
It's actually you get
the negative when
you flip them.
The distributive
property works
like we usually would.
>> The, you can pull in
scalars to either vector.
Number four is saying
something quite important.
>> That when you
take the cross
product with a vector is
always orthogonal to
any of the vectors.
>> So the cross
product of u and v is
orthogonal to u because
the dot product of that
vector with you is 0.
>> The cross product of u
and v is orthogonal to
V because the dot
product with v is 0.
The cross product of
a vector with itself is 0,
the cross-product
with the 00.
And then number seven
is something called
the triple scalar product,
which we'll see
in another slide.
>> So here we have
the cross-product and
its relationship
to the angle.
>> And this
formula here says
that the magnitude of
the cross-product,
we can find that by
taking the magnitude of
the two vectors themselves
times the sine of the
angle between them.
>> And this picture
here shows two vectors,
u and v, and the angle
between them is theta.
>> And we can use
trigonometry to
see that the height of
this parallelogram,
actually the magnitude of
u times the sine of theta.
We can find the areas.
Since we have the height
and we have the base,
we can find the area
of this parallelogram and
it actually turns out to be
the magnitude of
the cross-product.
So this is a really
important idea,
is that the magnitude
of the cross product is
the area of the
parallelogram
formed by the two vectors.
So anytime you're trying
to find area of, of,
let's say a parallelogram
or a triangle,
which is half of
a parallelogram
in you can use the
cross-product.
There's something called
the right hand rule,
which talks about
the direction
of the cross product.
In the previous
slide, we are talking
about the magnitude
of the cross-product.
>> What about
its direction?
>> So what you do,
the right hand
rule says that
if you take your hand or
your right hand and you
pointed in the direction
of the first vector,
and then you move it to
the direction of
the second factor.
The cross-product is in
the direction that your
thumb is pointing.
And we can see that if
you do that with
this picture,
that your thumb
should be pointing in
a direction orthogonal
to both u and
v. So here is
an important example using
the cross product
to find an area.
So you're giving a triangle
in space like this,
and we'll put points on
them so you can
find the points.
Now if we're going to use
the idea of the
cross product,
which would be to find
the parallelogram
formed by the sides of
these two sides
of the triangle.
And then just take half of
that to find the area,
we need to have
it in three-dimensional
space.
Because remember,
the cross-product
is something you
can only do with
vectors in
three-dimensional space.
So you can just do is
imagine the triangle
and this example
sitting in three-dimensional
space with
the z-axis with z
values being 0.
>> Okay?
>> So that's just the
same thing as adding
zeros to the end of
the coordinates.
>> Then we can find the
vectors a b and a c.
>> So a b would be
the vector that
goes from a to b.
A c would be the
vector from a to
C. And then we find
those two vectors,
and 1-1-0 and
two negative 10,
we can find the
cross product
of those two vectors.
And we see that
turns out to be
00 and negative three,
which is actually
not surprising
because since the vector
AB and AC both lie
in the xy plane,
parallel to the xy plane.
We know that the
cross-product is
going to be
orthogonal to that.
So it points actually
purely in the z direction,
in this case in the
negative z direction.
So then the magnitude of
the cross-product is
just the magnitude
of this vector 00,
negative three,
which is three.
And then we remember
that the magnitude of
this cross product
is the area of
the parallelogram formed
these two vectors,
which is just two copies
of this triangle.
>> And so the area
of the triangle is
just three has ok,
so the a parallel pipe,
it, a parallel pipe,
it is a
three-dimensional shape
that's formed by
three vectors.
>> And it's really
just like a box
that's been squished
a little bit.
And there's a really
convenient way to find
the volume of
such a shape with
cross products.
And that involves
this thing called
the triple scalar product.
So if you take any one of
these three vectors and
then take the dot product
with the cross product
of the other two.
>> What that gives is
the volume of that box.
>> And that actually
has important
consequences for
finding the
distance between
two lines in
three-dimensional
space and so on.
So this is an
important idea,
the triple scalar product.
>> Another application is
torque from physics,
torque is roughly a measure
of turning force
applied to an object.
>> So you, we have
a force vector
F and then we have
some kind of
lever vector l.
>> Okay?
>> And so the force is
what you get, I'm sorry,
the torque is what
we get when we take
the cross product of
the force with the lever.
Now if we think about
the equations
that we just had
in the previous slides,
the cross product has
the most magnitude when
the angle is 90 degrees,
because the sine of
90 degrees is one.
So that means that
the parallelogram
is really a rectangle.
So you're going to have
the most torque when
the force is applied
perpendicular to the lever,
which actually
aligns with what we
would normally think as
having the mouse torque.
>> So this is
the formula that
we use in physics
for torque.
>> And usually we take
the magnitude of this
defined how large
the torque is