This is a short video
on Section 13.7,
triple integration with
cylindrical and
spherical coordinates.
For cylindrical
coordinates,
cylindrical coordinates
are a way to
describe points in
three-dimensional space.
What they really
are is just
a kind of a combination of
our polar coordinates in
the x and y directions.
And then we just
have a comma z,
where z is just the
normal rectangular
coordinate.
That means is if
we have a point
x comma y comma z
sitting in
three-dimensional space,
it's cylindrical.
>> Cylindrical
coordinates would
be an r theta z,
where r is again, it's the,
the radius in the x,
y plane, which is
the square root
of x squared
plus y squared.
>> And then just as
polar coordinates,
it's angle theta is
found by taking the tangent
of theta is y over x,
and then Z is just Z as it
would be with
rectangular coordinates.
Again, we can go
back the other way.
If we're given a point
in cylindrical coordinates,
we can find it is a
rectangular coordinates.
Again, Z is to Z,
but where we can
get back x and y
by taking x equal to r
cosine theta and y
equal to r sine theta.
So let's describe
the surfaces
given in cylindrical
coordinates.
We have r equal to one,
theta equal to
pi over three,
and Z equal to two.
R equals to one is
just a circle of radius
one and the x, y plane.
>> But if the
z value is f3,
z is allowed to
be anything.
>> So r equals
to one gives us
the green cylinder here.
Theta equals two pi
over three is normally
a ray that's pointing
at an angle of 60 degrees.
Well, here, because
we have, again,
z is allowed to
take on any value
that actually gives
us a half-plane.
So starting here at the
z-axis and extending
60 degrees out in the,
in the x, y plane.
>> Then z equals to two.
>> Z equals to do describes
exactly the same plane that
we'll describe in
rectangular coordinates.
Here's the horizontal plane
that goes through
the 0.002.
>> We can do triple
integrals where
the integration of a
triple integral is
with respect to
r d z d r d theta.
>> And the reason for
that is very similar
to the same reason
we have the r d,
r d theta for
polar coordinates.
>> Now we just have
it also a DZ here.
>> We're given a solid
represented in
the picture here,
which is bounded by the
plane z equals to 0.
And its top is
the square root of
four minus x squared plus
y squared plus three.
And then also the cylinder
at x squared plus
y squared equals
two for the region has
a density function
given here.
And we want to be able to
find the mass
of this region.
So we can change things to
polar coordinates,
say some,
Sorry, to cylindrical
coordinates because the
Cylindrical coordinates
are a convenient way
to describe what's
going on here.
So in our density function,
x squared plus y squared
becomes r squared.
Z is just Z n plus one.
The region of
integration from
below here is the
disc of radius two.
And in polar coordinates,
let's just given
as r equal to two.
>> So that allows
us to set up our
integral here.
>> We're going to
integrate with respect to
z d z from z equals
to 0 to the top.
>> While the top of this is
defined by this
function here.
>> Here we can see
the limit of
integration where
minus x squared minus y
squared becomes
minus r squared.
Then d r, where r is
going to go from 0 to
two and theta is
all the way around
0 to two pi.
>> And then this just
becomes an iterated
integral where we
integrate with
respect to each
variable one at a time.
>> So about 276 grams.
>> We also have
spherical coordinates,
just another way
of describing
points in
three-dimensional space.
>> Here, a spherical
coordinate
is usually used with
these three letters are
rho, theta and phi.
Rho is the distance
to the origin.
>> Okay? If phi is
the angle with the
positive x-axis,
I'm sorry, theta is
the angle to
the positive x.
>> I just noticed
that theta would be
the same as in
polar coordinates.
>> And then phi is
the angle from the
positive z-axis.
>> And every point in
three-dimensional space
can be described
uniquely this way.
>> If we have the
point given as
just a regular x comma y
comma z rectangular
coordinate.
We can get the spherical
coordinates with the
following equations.
>> You notice that row is
just the distance formula.
And then since theta is the
same as in polar
coordinates,
it's equation
stays the same.
And then the only one that
requires a little
bit more thought
here is how we
can find phi.
>> But notice
that phi here is
the vertical distance
from the x, y plane.
>> So it actually forms
a triangle here
with the z axis.
And we can do some trig to
see that this
is the formula.
>> Now,
given a point in
spherical coordinates,
we can recovers x, y,
and z with the
following equations.
>> Here's a summary of the
different coordinate
systems and the ways in
the formulas to get
between one and the other.
The main thing here is that
it's not trying to
complicate things,
but certain regions and
three-dimensional
space and functions
have different symmetries.
And the different
coordinate systems
that we might use help us.
I'll take advantage of
those similar symmetries
to make the
computation easier.
So he wanted to
describe the services
given in spherical
coordinates.
Here we have rho
equal to one,
theta is equal to
pi over three,
and v is equal to pi over
six fecal to one
or all the points
at distance one
from the origin.
Well, that's just
a sphere, unit
sphere theta equals
pi over three.
That's actually
identical to
the plane that we saw
on the cylindrical
coordinates.
And then here we have 5y
is equal to pi over six.
Well, those are
all the points
whose angle with
the positive z-axis is
30 degrees, that
gives us a cone.
>> How to buckle under
integrals are defined.
>> We have to understand
how the volume of
a piece with respect
to changes in rho,
theta and fi
would look like.
And here we can use
some trig to see that
any change in volume is
going to be the
change in rho times
rho times the change in
phi in this direction.
And then rho times
this row times
the sine of phi
times the theta.
And that gives us the
way to talk about how
volume changes with respect
to its spherical
coordinates,
with respect to
small changes
in rho, theta and phi.
Finally, we end with
the volume of a sphere.
We've seen this in
various other ways,
but with spherical
coordinates it's,
it works out in a
way where the math
is as easy as possible.
>> So here, if we have
a sphere of radius r,
we can integrate
rho from 0 to r,
then integrate theta
from 0 to two pi and
integrate v from 0 to pi.
>> And if we do
this integration with
as iterated integral,
we didn't exactly four
pi over three R cubed,
which is what
we know as the
volume of a sphere.