Hi, class.
>> Let's take a look at
a quick overview
of section 12.1.
Now we're going to be
looking at functions of
two real variables before.
And calculus,
we've been looking
functions of a single
real variable.
Now our inputs to
our functions are
going to be
points x comma y.
Or in the case
of a function of
three variables points
x comma, y comma z.
We can graph a function
of two variables with
a single output like this.
>> Every input is
some x comma y in
the x, y plane.
>> We put that point
into the function
that gives
us a z value as an output.
So that describes
a surface.
If we have a nice
continuous function like
this in
three-dimensional space,
you can be asked a lot
of the same types of
questions that we
had in calculus.
One, about finding
domains and
ranges of functions of
two or more variables.
In this case, let's
find the domain of
a function given here.
>> To find the
domain, remember it's
all points x comma y where
the functions has
a valid output.
>> So we can't
take the square
root of a negative,
but we can take
the square root
of any non-negative number.
So that is the constraint
that we're going to
use to find this.
>> First we can
find the function's
value at 0 comma 0.
>> That's just
sticking 0 comma
0 into the function
x is 0, y is 0.
Solve, we get one.
>> So a point on
the graph of this function
is 0 comma 0 comma one.
>> Good.
>> Now the domain
is determined
by the collection of
points where the
function is defined.
>> And this function is
defined as long as the part
underneath the square root
is greater than
or equal to 0.
So that gives us
the following
inequality here.
We could shuffle
things around
a bit and notice that
our inequality
is very similar
to the standard
form of an ellipse.
In fact, if this
was x squared over
nine plus y squared over
four equals to one.
It would just be an
ellipse in standard form.
But the less
than or equal to
one means that the x
and y values are
allowed to be smaller.
>> So it's actually
describing
the interior of an ellipse.
>> So the set of
points where x squared
over nine plus y
squared over four
is less than or
equal to one is
the inside of this ellipse.
>> So that's going
to be the domain of
the function for the range.
>> We want to look at
all possible
z-values achieved
by putting in those x
values in the domain.
>> And for that it's
maybe a little bit
trickier to see.
>> But if we put
the 0 comma 0,
in which we did,
we got one.
>> And that's actually the
biggest that
we'll ever get.
>> Because you can
see underneath
the function f,
we have 12x minus
positive number.
Positive number.
>> So any value of x
and y that's not 0,
you're gonna be subtracting
a positive quantity here.
>> And which is gonna
be less than one.
So one's the biggest
that we can get
and 0 is the
smallest we can get.
So that gives us a range of
all of the numbers
from 0 to one.
We can graph the function.
And a 3D graphing utility
that's just kind of
satisfying to be
able to do to,
to see that all of our
analysis is working.
Oftentimes we want to look
at our three-dimensional
surfaces or
graphs of are functions of
two variables by looking at
are what are called
level curves.
>> And these are the
cross sections for
various constant
slices of z.
>> So the idea of
a level curve or
a contour map is
actually quite
familiar to anyone who's
looked at a map
for hiking, like
a mountain map.
>> So you have a map
that looks like this,
and we have these,
these lines in it.
>> And the lines
correspond to
places where the altitude
is not changing.
So if you were to walk
along these lines,
you will have the
same z value.
And when the lines are
very close together,
that means that if
you were to walk
perpendicular to the
lines are orthogonal,
it will be very steep.
>> If the lines
are far apart,
that means you
will be walking
a great distance in
order to achieve
that same level
of altitude that
you would be
over here if you were to
walk a short distance
to gain that level
of altitude,
which means it's
relatively flat,
relatively flat down here,
relatively steep over here.
>> So the way we talk
about kind of analyze
three-dimensional surfaces
is very much like
how we look at Level curves
and topographical map.
So we can take a look
at the same function
again and look at
its level curves.
>> That means taking
various zi values,
and we'll call them C at
a constant level,
constant steps.
So in our case,
our RZ steps
are at length of 0.2 each.
>> And we just
set our output
equal to those values.
And that gives us all
of these different curves
in the XY plane.
But remember the curve,
curves in the x,
y plane correspond to
the cross-sections
at these different
z values.
>> We can shuffle things
around a little bit
and see that
these are really
just ellipses
and they are
concentric ellipses.
>> If we graph
each of these,
what we see is
what's called a
contour plot of
the function.
>> And this is
a visualization
of that three-dimensional
graph, right, as F,
as we sliced cross-sections
with planes parallel
to the xy axis,
we can see towards the edge
that the graph is
rather steep in
the z direction
and then toward
the middle graph is
rather flat in
the z direction.
Can also discuss functions
of three variables.
We can, of course graph
a function of
three variables.
>> We need four
dimensions for that.
>> But if we look at
its level curves,
we can set the
function z values to
certain constant values and
then graph those surfaces
in three-dimensional space.
So here we're
looking at the level
curves of this function.
X squared over nine plus
y squared over four plus x
squared over
four equals to,
I think in this case, 123