Let's look at a short
overview of section
12.4 on
differentiability and
the total derivative.
Recall from calculus
one that a differential
is an expression
that helps us
discuss small changes
in a variable.
We saw that if y is f of x,
we can write d y is
f prime of x, dx.
And then we interpret
dx as a small change in
x and d y
as the corresponding
small change in y.
>> For small changes in x.
>> The same kind of
situation is true
for functions of
two variables,
but now we have
a new function,
a new variable z,
that changes with small
changes and x and y.
And we find the
total differential
by adding up
these two parts.
So let's find the two, the
total differentiable
dysfunction.
>> We can find the
partial derivatives
with respect to x
and respect to y.
>> And then it's
just a matter
of simply writing down
those partial
derivatives attached to
the corresponding
differentials dx and dy y.
>> What is DZ?
Anyways? Remember that
we really want
to know if a,
if x and y change
a little bit,
how much does d, how
much does z change?
Well, d z tells
us how much it
changes if the function
is perfectly flat
at that point.
>> So it's like a
linear estimate
of what the change
in x and y s.
>> So we want to use DZ
to estimate changes in Z.
Just to be clear,
the actual change
in the z value we usually
write as delta z,
but we want to estimate
delta z with TZ,
which is the
estimated change.
>> Using the total
differential,
we can write the actual
change delta z as DZ.
>> There's sort of
a local approximated change
plus some error in the
x and y directions.
So a function is
differentiable
is as DX and DY
get really small.
Also, these
errors get really
small and the technical
description is here.
But that's essentially
what's happening is
that the function
can be a locally
approximated by
a tangent plane
by flat surface.
And that flat
surface means that
DZ is a good approximation
for delta Z.
We want to keep
the logic of
continuity and
differentiability straight.
And we want to
remember that if
a function is
differentiable,
then it indeed has
to be continuous,
but it's not true the
other way around.
>> A function
is continuous.
>> It may not be
differentiable.
A function can have
jagged parts on
the surface where
the derivative
doesn't exist but
still be continuous,
we can show that
something is
differentiable, however,
by looking at the
partial derivatives
and showing that
they are continuous.
>> So let's find, let's use
the differential to
make an approximation.
>> So here we're given
a function z equals
the square root of
x times sine of y.
And we want to
approximate at
the function at four
comma one comma 0.8.
Now 4.10.8 aren't
particularly nice numbers,
but they are very
close to the
0.4 comma pi over four.
>> And if we had four
comma pi over four,
that's actually
an easy point
to evaluate a dysfunction.
So we would like
to, since we can
find the functions value
at a nearby point,
we would like to use
the differential to find
with that change must
be in the function
between four pi
over 44.10.8.
>> Okay? So we can find
the differential
by taking the
partial derivatives
of the function here.
>> We can find the
partial derivatives
with respect to x
and respect to y.
>> And then we
evaluate at the point
that we can easily find,
which is four comma
pi over four.
>> And that gives us
these values here.
And then we have the
changes in the function.
We know that to go
from four to 4.1,
we have a delta of 0.10.8
pi over four is about 0.05.
Therefore, the
approximate value
of the function is
the functions value at
the nearby point plus
this small change.
In the small change
we're measuring with
the total
differential that we
found above at this point.
So we get our estimation
to be about 1.4531