Hello and welcome
to a video on
calculus and vector
valued functions.
This is an overview
of Section 11.2.
This is a particularly
midi section
and it shows how we can
extend pretty much the
basics of calculus.
122 are new objects
of vector valued functions.
First, let's
look at limits.
If we have the limit of
a vector valued function,
it's defined in
the normal epsilon
delta away.
Now the notation here
can be somewhat confusing,
but what it's really saying
is straightforward,
especially if we
look at the picture.
If we're going to
take the limit of
a vector valued function
that may be changing,
then the limit actually
approaches a
another vector.
If for any circle of size
epsilon around
the distance between
the vectors,
that the vectors will
eventually be that
distance apart.
So let me begin
the animation to show
you what I mean.
>> So in this picture,
the green arrow is r of t.
>> The green arrow
is changing and
the blue arrow is
the limit vector.
>> And what we're
trying to understand
is what does it mean for
the green arrow to
approach the blue arrow?
What it means for the
green arrow to approach
the blue arrow means
that the distance
between the blue arrow
and the green
arrow given by
the red arrow
eventually has
magnitude less
than epsilon.
Now, epsilon was
arbitrarily given,
so I made a circle
of size epsilon.
But maybe you're not
convinced and
you say, Well,
make epsilon smaller
and shrink that circle.
>> And then if it's
still true that
eventually the red arrow
is within that
small circle.
>> That's how we conclude
that the limit of
the green arrow is going
to the blue arrow.
>> Okay?
>> So I'll play
this one more.
>> Time limits in
vectors can occur in
sort of more
ways than we do.
>> And we look at limits
in real valued functions,
can think there's more room
to spin around and
things like that.
The vector of the limit of
a vector valued function
can be found by
taking the limits
of the components.
So really this is just
a sneaky way of saying
now that we're going
to find limits
of vector valued functions,
we're just finding
two limits at once
for looking at R2 or three
limits at once and R3.
So all of the
properties of limits in
the techniques for taking
limits applies here.
May you have, you have them
occurring in each
coordinate separately.
Here's a vector-valued
function,
and it's asking
us to find the
limit as t goes to
0 using the
previous theorem.
The limit as t goes to
0 of the vector valued
function is the
same as the limit
as t goes to
0 of each individual
component.
>> And now we just have
some limit problems.
>> Remember, the
limit as t goes to
0 of sine t over
t is that famous
result where it's one.
And you could use
L'Hopital's rule to see
that the limit as
t goes to 0 of
a polynomial,
here is 0. Melody
as t goes to 0.
Cosine t. Since T
is continuous at 0,
you simply can plug 0
in and get the
value of one.
We can also talk
about continuity for
vector valued functions or
functions continuous
if it's a limit
exists at every
point and is
actually equal to the value
of the function
at that point.
So the same as in
Calculus One and Two,
except now our functions,
our vector valued
functions,
not real valued functions.
In this animation, I
show a discontinuity.
So we have
a vector valued function
spinning around
the circle but
suddenly moves,
so it's discontinuous.
The way you can
check continuity of
a vector valued function
under some circumstances
is to just look at
the continuity of
each component and then
its continuity in
the same sense
as Calculus one.
The derivative is differ.
A vector valued
function is defined
also similar to
calculus one.
It's the limit of the
difference quotient.
So the derivative
at a point
c is the limit as
h goes to 0 of the
difference quotient.
The derivative function at
any point t is
given by the same,
the notation that
we'll use for
derivatives of vector
valued functions,
pretty much the same as
real valued functions,
except we have
a vector arrow
over the vector
value function.
It's nice that
the derivative
of a vector valued function
is the derivative
of the components.
And this is actually
an extension of the limit.
Remember, derivatives
are just limits.
And this is just
saying that the,
we can take the derivative
in each compounded
because the
limit works at
each component.
What about vector
value functions
of three dimensions?
Here's an example we'll
be seeing several times.
What we have is
a simple helix,
cosine t, sine t and t.
>> Now we want to
compute the derivative.
>> So given that
that's cosine t,
sine t t, you
take the derivative of
each function separately.
And I'm, in this sketch,
what you see,
the derivative
is the red arrow.
The yellow arrow is
the vector valued
function itself,
and the red arrow
is the derivative.
And you might be
already noticing
some interesting
properties of
the derivative of
a vector valued
function. It's
the velocity.
Taking derivatives
of vector valued
functions allow us to
find the tangent to the
graph at the point.
And then we can find
the tangent line
to the graph at
a point where we're given,
here is the equation
for a tangent line.
And you should notice
its similarity to
the equation of
the linearization
of a function at a point
from calculus one,
you have the mesial at,
at the value C, you have
the initial value plus
scaled by the
direction vector,
the slope, what we
normally use in
calculus one.
So looking at our previous
example, cosine t,
sine t t, we can find
the equation of
the tangent line
at pi over two.
We simply put the values
into this function.
And as you can see
from the graph,
it looks like
the tangent line
exactly how we
would expect it.
Finally, smoothed
vectors are
vectors that have
a derivative.
So we know that
not all vectors
have a derivative.
>> Some R, R2
pointy or jerky.
>> The derivative
is continuous on
the interval and the
derivative is never 0.
Some important properties
of derivatives,
these are things that we
really get used
to in calculus.
One is that the
derivative of
a sum is the sum of the
derivatives and so on.
We can pull constants out.
>> Maybe the
surprising thing here
is that in properties 345,
the product rule
applies when we have
normal multiplication
and the dot product
and the cross product.
>> So that's a
nice, we don't have
to memorize anymore rules.
We have the product rule
that applies to all three,
and then the chain rule
applies in a similar way.
An important application
of physics is that
a vector that has
constant length,
so it might be moving,
but the length is the same,
is orthogonal to
its derivative.
This is how we describe
circular motion.
Now, integration, we have
a vector valued function.
We want to be able to
talk about its integral.
And just like in calc two,
its integral is defined as
the limit of these
Riemann sums.
The only different is that
each of the summands
in the Riemann sum is
now a vector value,
the integral, integral,
the vector valued function.
The components are just the
integrals of
the components.
>> And each
component we have
a integral that's just
like an integral.
>> And calculus to this
is an important example
that relates to physics.
Now I'm going to use
a language that is,
hasn't really
been introduced
in the text yet,
but it's really common
in a problem like this.
If we're given a vector
equation with r,
r of t, we'll call
that position.
>> Its derivative is
velocity and its derivative
is acceleration.
>> So in this example,
we're actually given an
acceleration vector.
We're given an
initial position
and an initial velocity.
And what we're
asked to find is to
find a vector equation
for the position itself.
So given a vector equation
for the acceleration,
we're actually
can find a vector
equation for the position.
First, we take
the acceleration
r double prime, and
we integrate it.
And we integrate
each coordinate
and we're left with
some constants
of integration.
But here is where we can
use the fact
that we're given
that the initial
velocity at 0 is 530.
>> So we can set this
vector expression
equal to 530.
>> And that allows us to
solve for the coefficients.
Then we can put
the coefficients
back in to r prime of
t. And that gives
us our update equation
for velocity.
So now we have a vector
that describes the
velocity in terms
of t. And then
we do the same thing
again to find position.
We integrate the velocity,
you integrate
each component,
we're left with constants
of integration,
but we're given a vector
of the initial velocity.
So we can set that equal
to negative seven,
negative one, to solve
for the constants.
In this case, we get
constants negative 70.
>> To put those back
in that we put
into the expression
for the position.
>> And then finally we get
our position vector.
>> The arc length
of a vector
is sound with the
following expression.
>> It's the integral of
the magnitude of the
velocity vector.