Let's take a look
at parameterized
services and service area.
In section 14.5, we've
already seen
parameterizations of curves,
curves in
two-dimensional space
and curves in
three-dimensional space.
Curve is really just
like a one-dimensional line
that is living in
a two-dimensional
flat space
or maybe moving
around in
three-dimensional space.
But either way, the setup
is a vector
valued function,
where every point
along the curve
corresponds to the
terminal value of
that vector valued
function for
some value in it's
parametrized interval.
So as T ranges,
for example, between 01,
every terminal point along
that vector R corresponds
to some point
along the curve.
We want to do the
same thing now,
not for linear curves
in two-dimensional,
three-dimensional
space, but surfaces.
To talk about surfaces
of two dimension,
two dimensional surfaces
in three-dimensional space,
we need to have
the concept of
Orient ability.
So 4N double means that any
field of normal vectors
that we define
on the surface,
that it has to
vary continuously.
And that's sort of
hard to think about.
So what we usually
do is we look at
a non oriental surface
and think about what's
happening there.
A famous example is
the Mobius band.
If you take a piece
of paper to strip and
turn it to a 108
to turn one in
280 degrees and then
glue it back to each other.
What you have is the
following picture.
And any way you define
a field of normal vectors
along the surface,
if you start on one part
and traverse along
all the way around
back to that same
pot spot we end up
getting is a normal
vector pointing
in the opposite direction.
So that means is that this
surface doesn't
really have an,
have a two different sides.
You really has a, was
a one-sided surface.
Well, we, we want to
avoid that problem.
We want to have services
that are two-sided.
So let's parameterize
a surface
given as the graph
of the function z
equals x squared
plus two y squared
over this disk
of radius two.
We have to be
careful because we
might want to parameterize
this service of you
going between
negative two into V,
going between negative 22
and then just let
the x value b,
you let the y value BV put,
put v and u into
the function to find
the corresponding z value.
And then we have
a parameterization
of the surface.
It's true it is, but it's
the service
above the square
where x goes
between negative
22 and y goes
between negative 22.
It's not the surface
above the desk.
So since we have
a disk with
circular symmetry,
where we need to do
is use something like polar
coordinates with
the variables u
and v to describe
our location
within the desk.
So if we let u be
a variable that
describes the angle
around the desk,
and we let v be the,
the polar value,
the radius.
Then what we can do is
describe any point
within the disk with
following parameterization
to v cosine
nu and 2V sine u.
So for any value
u between 02 pi,
you are at some angle
around the desk.
And for any value v
from 0 to one. We're
located to v distance
away from the center.
So every point in that
desk corresponds to
a single u comma v
in these intervals.
Then what you do is use
the hex value of two
v cosine knew the
y-value of two,
the sign you and put those
into the function
for z to find
the corresponding
z value in
terms of u and v.
And therefore,
our parameterization
of this particular surface
above the desk
is given here.
This is the trick for
parameterizing surfaces,
where we are trying
to prioritize over
a particular region,
which can be difficult.
So what we do is
if your region is
the x value is bounded
between two
constant values,
but the y-values
bounded, let's say,
between two functions of x.
Then you can use this trick
to write down and
nice parametrization
of the surface.
Let's parameterize
this cylinder.
So this is a cylinder,
it's not exactly round.
You have it's higher
here than it is wide.
So one way to
think about it is
any point on the surface
of this cylinder,
He's really defined
by two directions.
There's the direction
that's sort of
the angle around
the skewer.
Here. The y-axis is,
goes through the center and
then you have a direction
which is along the y-axis
or the length of
the cylinder.
And that's sort of
the inspiration
to use the following
parametrization.
If we let u correspond
to an any value between
02 pi then and
for any fixed y,
a location along
that slice that's
parallel to the z-axis is
described by cosine nu two
sine U in the z components.
So that's nice. So
for any fixed y,
we can describe any point
along the outside of
the cylinder that way.
But then we just for
the y value will
parameterize it with v
going between negative 11,
because those defined
the endpoints
of the cylinder
that will describe
the location
lengthwise of the cylinder.
So any point on the surface
now can be described
with this parameterization.
We also want to
be able to find
the surface area of
our parameterizations.
To do this, we'll use,
it's kinda the
same idea that we
used to find areas
of planar curves.
So if we had a
region in the plane,
we could find the area
of that region by
taking the double
integral of
the value one
over the region.
And the whole
idea is we find
the area by summing
up little pieces of
the area da over
the region.
Only the difference is
now we're going to sum
up little pieces of
surface area ds.
If we have a
function and we
take a look at a small
piece of it's graph,
we can pull out a
tiny little rectangle
that approximates
the service area.
And we'll remember if that,
if we have two vectors that
are tangent to the surface,
then the magnitude of
the cross-product gives us
the area of the
parallelogram.
So we use the magnitude
of the cross product of
these two tangent
vectors to
estimate the surface
area and a small piece.
And then what we do is we
take the pieces to be
smaller and smaller
and smaller,
add them all up.
And that's how we're
going to define
our service area integral.
So let's take a look
at the same example
that we just looked
at with the cylinder.
We have the parametrization
that we found.
Let's find the
surface area.
The first thing we
need to do is take
the derivatives of
our parametrization.
So you take the
derivative with
respect to u of all
three components,
take the derivative
with respect to
v of all three components.
We find the cross product
of those two vectors.
Then we find the magnitude
of that cross product.
And then we write down
the surface area integral.
We know that our
function of the mind to
the cross product
we just found.
And since we
are integrating
u from 0 to two pie
and v from 0 to one.
That gives us our
limits of integration
and we can calculate
that integral.
And it turns out
to be about 53.6