Hello and welcome
to a short video
on the dot product.
This is an overview
of section 10.3.
>> The dot product
definition is this.
If you have two
vectors, U and D,
then the dot product
is defined as
the sum of the product
of the respective
coordinates.
>> So if you have
two vectors,
U and V in two dimensions,
you just multiply U1, V1,
multiply u2, v2,
add them up.
>> And the same goes with
three-dimensional
vectors or
four-dimensional vectors
for that matter.
>> So the dot product is
relatively easy to find.
>> Let's find
the dot product
for these two vectors.
The vector x dot
product with
the vector y is
equal to this case,
two times negative one
plus negative two times
0 plus five times three.
>> And that gives
us negative two
plus 0 plus 15,
which is 13.
Notice that the
dot product is
a way to multiply
two vectors,
except the answer that
you get is a number.
>> So that's pretty
important. When you take
a vector dot product with
another vector,
you get a number.
And what that number
is very important.
And it ends up telling
us information
about the angle between
the two vectors.
>> So the properties of
the dot product r here,
and these are things
to just sort of
casually be aware of.
>> The commutative
property means we can take
the dot product in
either order and
get the same thing.
It distributes the way that
multiplication typically
distributes with numbers.
But keep in mind that
these things are vectors.
Scalars behave nicely
with the dot product.
>> You can take a scale.
>> If you multiply
a scalar times
the dot product
of two vectors,
that's just the
same as multiplying
the scalar times one
of those two vectors,
the 0 vector, which is
a unique vector
that's just zeros,
multiply it times
any vector,
and it has a dot
product of 0.
And number five is
especially important.
>> It says that
the dot product
of a vector with
itself is the
magnitude squared.
>> So this is
actually really
nice because
it's another way
for us to find the
magnitude of a vector.
So how does the dot-product
relate to an angle?
>> That's the width?
>> This equation here, so
just says that the dot
product is equal to
the norm or the magnitude
of the two vectors
multiplied
together times the
cosine of the angle
between them.
And an important
thing is to
understand where that
formula comes from.
>> And I won't go
through it on
the video here,
but feel free to contact
me with questions.
But if you have two
vectors, u and v,
what you can do is
look at this picture
here where you
have u minus v And
that built a triangle.
>> And you can
apply the law of
cosines to that
triangle from trig,
and you get exactly
this formula.
So that means if you can
solve for cosine theta,
and then you take
the cosine inverse.
We have a formula to find
the angle between
two vectors.
Keep in mind that
the cosine inverse
function is
a function that
always returns
an angle between 0 and pi.
So when you're finding
the angle between
two vectors,
you can of course look at
the shortest angle, right?
And then you can look at
though angle that
goes all the way
around this angle
that if you use
this formula,
this will always give
you the angle that's
the shortest angle
between two vectors.
And important
concept is the
one of orthogonal vectors.
So two vectors are
orthogonal if their
dot product is 0.
And orthogonal means it's
the general idea
of perpendicular.
So if two vectors
are orthogonal,
if you take the dot
product, you get 0.
So it's a really nice,
easy way to check to see if
two vectors are
perpendicular or not.
>> Now if their
dot product is 0,
let's just go back
to this slide
and take a look at
the formula here for
the cosine of theta.
>> If the dot
product is 0, that
means the cosine
of the angle
between them is equal to
0 divided by
something which is 0.
So if the cosine
of an angle is 0,
we know from trig that that
means that the angle has to
be 90 degrees
or 270 degrees.
>> But because
we're looking at
the smaller angle,
it's 90-degree angle.
So the dot product being 0
means that the angle
is 90 degrees.
>> So they really are
perpendicular
in that sense.
What are some examples
of orthogonal vectors?
>> So that's kinda fun
to play around with.
>> I'll give you
just a couple
fun ones to look at.
You could look
at the vector
in two dimensional space,
right, with 11 going
one in the x direction,
one in the y direction.
>> And you could
look at the vector y
going one in the
x direction,
negative one in
the y direction.
>> And we can
see if we take
the dot product of these,
we get one times one
plus one times negative
one equals to 0.
>> So those are
two vectors in
two dimensional space
whose dot product is
0. And there are
many others.
Any two vectors who meet
at a 90 degree angle
have a dot product of
0 and R orthogonal.
An important idea
in vectors is
that a vector projection,
especially in
physics if you have
forces going in
two directions.
So let's say you wanted
to pull an object in
the direction of v
in this picture.
>> But some things
in the way perhaps.
So you can only
pull it in the
direction of view.
You'd, you'd
want to know how
much of that force that
you're pulling from
you is actually
in the direction
that you care about.
>> So how much of
that is in the
direction of v?
And so that vector
is the blue vector
that you see here.
Which is written in this
strange way to probe
project the
projection PRO J
underscore V. And then you,
so the underscore,
the vector that's
here in the subscript
is the one that you're
projecting onto.
So this is an
important vector.
Whenever you have
two other vectors,
you can, you can get
this vector from it.
>> Another important idea
with the dot product
is the orthogonal
decomposition.
>> So just like in
the previous slide,
we talked about the
projection of U on to V.
>> Well, that gives
us, that gives rise to
another vector
which is W here.
And we can see that
in our picture,
that if you take w,
If you take the
projection plus w,
you get you there.
If you take w plus
the projection,
you get you.
>> So what is, what
is this vector w?
>> Anyways, it is
u minus the
projection vector.
So this is a way of
writing the vector,
the vector u in two parts.
The part that's
parallel with V and
the part that's
perpendicular to B.
>> And this is
just as useful
because maybe V is
an important direction that
we're working with on a,
on a certain incline.
And we just want to
write everything
about you in terms
of that vector v.
>> And this formula
gives us a nice
way to do that.
>> One application for
dot product that's
very important
and in physics is
the concept of work.
>> And you might
know that work
is defined as force
times distance.
>> Now that we're
talking about
vectors, though,
we can talk about
work in a better way.
>> And we can talk
about work in a way
when we have force not
necessarily given in
exactly the direction
of the that we want.
>> So you can see
in this picture,
in this example, a box
is pushed along a ramp,
the raises over a
distance of 15 feet by
applying 50 pounds of
force as shown
in the figure.
Compute the work done well.
>> So we have a ramp
that's 15 feet long,
three feet high, and
then there's a box
sitting on it.
We'd like to
pull the box up,
but we can see that we're
pulling the box with
a force that's not really
parallel with the ramp.
It's being pulled up at
a 30 degree angle from
the, from the horizontal.
So without vectors, we
couldn't really
calculate the work here.
But because we can take
the vector projection of
F onto the direction
that we want.
>> Now the direction
of the ramp,
we get a nice
formula for that.
And it turns out, and I'm
the derivation
from the vector
projection two,
this formula is
in our book,
but it turns out
that you can
find this work
by just taking
the dot product
of the force
with the direction that
the work is being done.
So here in this case,
the work is just
the dot product of
the force with
the direction d.
>> And we can see
that the ramp
has a change in acts of
15 and a change
of y of three.
>> And that's what gives,
because our D vector,
and then we have
our force vector,
which is, it's
a force of 50,
but 3030 degrees of
that is in the x direction,
and it's a 30 degree angle.
So cosine of 30
is the portion in
the x direction.
Sine of 30 is of course
on the y direction.
So that gives us
this simple formula.
You can find the
cosine of 30 and
sine of 30 in the same
way we always do.
And trig multiply
both those times 50,
take the dot product and
we can see that
the total work
is 724.5 foot pounds.
So this is a
very convenient
formula for finding work.