Let's take a look
at Section 12.8,
which is on extreme values.
Now this slide has
a lot of information on it,
but let's try to
keep it simple.
A function has an
absolute maximum, right?
If it's point
x-naught, y-naught,
if it's bigger than
everywhere else in
the function has an
absolute minimum.
If it's less than
everywhere else.
And the function, it's
a relative maximum
if it's bigger
than everywhere
else in some
little neighborhood
of the point.
And similarly for
relative minimum,
the maximums and
minimums are
called extremis,
the point at which
the partial derivatives
are equal to 0,
which means those
tangent slopes
of those tangent
lines are 0,
which means the
function is sort
of locally flat
at that point,
are called critical points.
>> Or if, or if those
derivatives are
not defined in calculus.
>> One, if I point,
was a critical point,
if the derivative
was equal to,
the derivative was
equal to u equal to 0.
>> Or if it didn't exist in
calculus 3, x nought,
y nought is a
critical point
if its gradient is
equal to the 0 vector,
or it's gradient
does not exist.
Notice that the gradient
of the function has
really taken the place
of f prime from
calculus one.
And if we really
think about it,
f prime for a
single variable
really is just a
gradient as well.
Just a gradient of
a single dimension.
Let's find the
relative extrema
of a function.
So we can find the
partial derivatives,
set them equal to 0,
and then solve in
this case we get
the point two-thirds come
a 1 third and it's
a critical point.
>> Okay, so we found
the critical point
at two-thirds, 1 third.
>> But how do we
know that it's a
maximum or a
minimum or neither?
>> That's the tricky part.
>> We can just graph
it like I did here.
>> I put in the
value two-thirds,
1 third for x and y.
>> And then you can see
that it's the point on
the bottom of the graph
of the function here.
So it must be a minimum.
In general, you can
find whether or not
a critical point
is a maximum
or minimum by graphing it,
not always possible,
especially if
it's a function of more
than two variables.
We can use numerical
approximations,
which means just put
end points nearby into
the function and find what
its values are and see if
those values are above
or below your
critical value.
Or we can use
some more sophisticated
kind of factoring
or analysis to determine
that it's a minimum.
Now if you don't
have technology,
usually what we need to do
is some kind of analysis.
So with this
particular function,
we can notice that
the given function is
actually in the
form of a conic.
And you might recall
from precalculus that
iconic is an equation
of the following form.
And when you have a b term,
in our case, negative
one is the B term.
>> It's the, the part in
front of the next x, y.
>> That means it's
a rotated conic.
And you may not remember
this from pre calc,
but I'm just kinda
bringing it up as a way to
use some skills
from calculus
to determine whether
this might be a minimum.
So we identified as
iconic rotated conic.
And then there's this
formula says that
the rotation angle
must be the cotangent
of the difference in
a minus c divided
by b. In this case.
In this case,
a's minus C a 0.
The cotangent
theta equals to
0 means theta is
pi over four.
Then we have
rotation equations
where we actually change
the coordinate
system to make
the a conic that doesn't,
no longer has
the mixed term.
And I just went
ahead and did this.
And I see that if we
make that substitution,
our original function
becomes this new function,
which maybe looks messier
but actually is in
the standard form for any,
for every constant
value of z,
it's in the standard
form of an ellipse.
So the level curves of
our function are ellipses.
And if we, we
already saw the graph
of the function,
which is, it's our
parabola lloyd.
So a parabola lloyd
Is a function
whose level curves are
ellipses going up and
whose cross sections
with respect to
the axis z and
y-z planes are parabolas,
so therefore it
must be a minimum.
So this is a
way to use some
of our knowledge from
precalculus to
determine that,
to determine if whether
that critical point
is a minimum or not.
>> You can have
points where
the derivatives are both 0.
>> So it's, it's locally
flat at the point.
But depending on
which direction
you're facing,
it might be at
the bottom of
the well or it might
be at the top of
a hill K. So
that point is called
a saddle point.
Saddle point is defined by
the partial
derivatives exist and
are both 0, so it's flat.
And then in any little disk
around that point,
you can find values of the
function which are greater
than and you can
find values of
the function that are
less than that point.
So it's not a
maximum or minimum.
We want something like
the second derivative test
for functions of
two variables.
We have the second
derivative test, remember,
tells us something about
concavity of the function.
If it's concave up at
that critical point,
then we know it's
a minimum, right?
If it's concave down,
then it's a maximum.
While the credit,
the credit,
the concavity is determined
by the second derivative.
But with a function
of two variables,
you have many
second derivatives.
You have the derivatives
with respect
to x and y,
and y x, y and y ax.
It turns out that if
we were to approximate
our function of
two variables
by a quadratic, sort of.
So I'm like a Multivariable
Taylor series,
that this value d here,
which is the determinant
of a Hessian matrix,
which we don't, you can
feel free to look up.
But this value d is
that coefficient
in front of those.
Quadratic terms. So it's
describing concavity of
a function of two
variables in the same way
that f double-prime
does in a single variable.
And we can follow the
following rules here.
If at any point,
if d is positive,
now it's assuming
that we're
looking at a
critical point.
So you find the critical
points who put them.
And if d is positive,
that means it's
a max or a min.
T determines a max or min.
You can use the derivative,
the secondary
with respect to x
to look at its concavity in
the normal sense to
determine if it's a
minimum or positive.
Here at the second
derivative is
positive, then
it's a minimum.
If the second
derivative is negative,
it's a maximum.
If D is negative,
that means at a
saddle point,
if t is 0, we don't know.
We have to use some
other methods.
>> So here's an example.
>> Liver function.
>> We want to
determine whether it
has a relative maximum,
minimum, or a saddle point
at each of the
critical points.
>> So we can find the
critical points by
finding the gradient and
setting it equal to 0.
That gives us a
couple of equations.
Here we have a
critical point at
one comma two and
negative one comma two.
We can take the second
derivatives and plug
in the 0.1 comma two.
Now d is the
secondary with
respect to x times
the secondary with
respect to y.
So six times one
times negative
two then
minus the mixed partial
derivatives are 0 times 0.
That gives us negative
12, which is negative.
Since d is negative
at that point,
we know that it's
a saddle point.
>> Now we try negative
one comma two.
>> So six times
negative one
times negative two,
which is positive 12.
Again, we're
subtracting 0 with
the mixed partials,
so that's positive.
And then when you take
a look at the sign
of the second derivative,
select acts,
that's negative.
>> So this must be
a maximum from
calculus one.
>> Remember that
any kind of,
any different
continuous
differential function
on a closed interval,
she does maximum, minimum.
The reason why we spend so
much time talking about
closed bounded sets earlier
is that the same thing is
true for a function of
two variables defined over
a closed bounded set.
It must also have
a maximum minimum.
>> So let's take a
look at this example.
>> If we have
this function f,
and then we have
this triangular
region in its domain.
In this particular
region is given.
But the vertices negative
one to negative or
negative to 012,
negative two.
We'd like to know what
is the maximum and
the minimum values of
f over this
triangular region?
The strategy is to find
a relative maximum
or minimum on
the inside of the region.
And then we have to break
down the boundaries
individually and find
its relative maximum
or minimums on those.
And then that gives
us candidates
for what the maximum and
minimum of what it might be
over the entire region.
So on the interior,
we take the gradient
and set it equal to
0 and determine what
points that might be.
In this case, 0 comma
0 is the point
where the gradient
is equal to 0.
So 0 comma 0 is our first
candidate for a max or min.
>> Now we have
to break up the,
the boundary of
that triangle
into its various pieces.
>> There's, I
broke it up into
segment a, B, and C here.
So first on segment a,
if we substitute y
equals to negative
two into the
original equation,
into the, into the
original function.
>> What we've
done is review.
>> We reduced it to
a function of a
single variable.
Now we can find
its max or mins in
the same way that we
wouldn't calculus one.
In this case, this
is pretty clear.
This is a parabola
shifted up one,
so it's going to have
a minimum at x equals to 0.
But notice that this
is a line segment over
a closed interval,
negative one to two.
We also have to consider
the endpoints with
x equal to negative one
and x equal to two.
And for segment a, y is
always equal to
negative two.
So we have x equals to 0.
Negative 12 are
possible maximum
admins that gives,
it gives rise to
these three points.
So we're keeping track
of all of the points
that are candidates for
maximum ends with
a functions.
Now on Segment B, it's
a similar kind of
procedure that
the segment is
described with this line y
equals negative three
halves x plus one.
What we do is we
substitute that
back into the function for
y that gives us a
function of only x,
which is the following
quadratic function.
We can find its maximum
minimums using calculus.
>> Take the derivative,
set it equal to 0.
>> Turns out axes six
fifths and y is
negative four-fifths.
So now we have,
and then we have
the endpoints with
x equals to 0 and
x equals two.
And when x is equal to two,
we actually get
the same point
that we got before.
So the new candidates
are the points
0 comma, 1 sixth comma,
negative four-fifths in
segments C, it's done.
>> Similarly, you put y
equal to 3x plus one.
>> And for y,
substitute that in.
For f, take the derivatives
are equal to 0 and we
get the point
negative three,
a negative 1 eighth.
Now, all of the
points that we found,
we found seven of them.
00, negative one,
negative 20,
negative two to negative
two, negative three,
negative 1016, that's
negative four-fifths.
So Israel candidates for
the maximum into
the function.
So how do we determine
what is the max
or min of f?
Well, we'd put them
all into the
function c. Well,
we get the biggest one is
the maximum and the
smallest one is
the minimum.
In this case, the
largest one here
is at 29 fifths,
which is about 5.8.
>> And the point
where that occurs,
sixth, negative
four-fifths.
>> And then the
minimum is one record
at the 0 comma negative two