Let's take a
look at section
12.6 on directional
derivatives.
We've already seen
directional
derivatives when we
were introduced to
partial derivatives,
the derivative
of a function
f with respect to x.
We learned that was the
limit as h goes to 0,
the difference quotient
that we see here.
Notice that the plus h
is in the x component
of the function.
And when the derivative
with respect to y,
the plus h is in the y
component of the function.
So what's really going
on here is we are
approaching the
point x comma
y from the right,
assuming H is positive
in the first expression,
we're approaching from
above in the second.
So rarely are
finding a directional
derivative.
In a sense, we're
finding the rate
of change of
f from two different
directions.
Now we can try to
imagine that we
could try to
find the rate at which f is
changing from
any direction.
And that means that H,
If we add h and
both components and
a weight it corresponding
to the direction.
We said that these are
just two particular cases.
So how do we generalize it?
We can try to think of
the directional derivative
as coming from any
direction on the
unit circle.
So instead of one in
the X direction
and 0 in the y,
we can just
choose a point on
the unit circle
and U1 and U2.
And that's going to
show us how we can
approach the point x comma
y from any direction.
So the definition of
the directional derivative
is just this
expression here.
The important
thing here is that
the direction vector
is a unit vector,
must have length one.
An easy way to find
the directional
derivative is
the dot product between
the vector of partial
derivatives and
the direction vector that
is given by this
expression here.
This actually
requires proof
and isn't entirely obvious,
but we need to
arrive at this fact
from the limit definition,
we can write this sum
as a dot product of
these two vectors.
The vector of partial
derivatives is actually
a very important vector
that's called the gradient.
And if we suppress
the argument here,
we see that the
directional derivative can
be written in a really
nice, clean formula.
The directional
derivative of
f in the direction of
u is the gradient of
f dot product with
the direction vector.
Let's take a look
at an example.
So the first thing
we need to do is
to find the
direction vector.
So if we're trying
to find the
derivative at the 0.1
comma two in the
direction of the origin.
That leaves us with
this vector here
from the 0.1 comma
two to the origin.
But remember the
direction vector
has to be a unit vector.
So we need to scale
it by its magnitude.
In this case, it's
magnitude is square
root of five.
So that leaves us with
a vector of length one.
>> And we can see
that direction
vector that we're
trying to find,
the derivative is given
by this vector u.
We can find the
partial derivatives of
the function at the point
>> Then we can take the
definition of the
directional derivative,
which is the dot
product of the gradient
at one comma two with
the direction vector.
And we see in
this case that
it comes out to two root
five. So more in
the gradient.
The gradient is of
a function of
two variables,
is a vector in
two-dimensional space.
So the dimension of
the gradient is
actually the
same as the domain
of the function.
And you can see
from this picture
here that we have graphed
a certain function and
then we've graphed
the gradient,
corresponding
gradient vectors in
the domain of the
function below.
And the picture
kinda gives us
a Santos sense of what
these vectors are
telling us, right?
The, the direction of
the gradient vector
is somehow pointing
into the steepest direction
of increase of
the function.
And its magnitude is how
fast it's increasing.
So that is very
steep, that it's
a very long
gradient vector.
If it's relatively flat,
it's a short
gradient vector,
and we'll see
that in a second.
So there's some
natural questions.
And when you have a
function of two variables
at any particular point,
what direction is
the function
increasing? The moused?
What direction
is the function
increasing the least?
Or what functions are
decreasing the mouse?
And what directions are
there no change
in the variable?
So we take a look
at the formula
for the directional
derivative.
We can remember that
we have a formula for
the dot product
with respect
to the angle between
the two vectors.
So theta is the angle
between the gradient
and the direction.
Ready, we are
thinking about
being a particular point.
Then we get the
following formula here.
That the magnitude of
the gradient times
the magnitude of
the unit vectors times
the cosine of the
angle between them.
But u is a unit vector,
so it has length one.
So you can simplify
things a bit,
and this actually
tells us quite a
bit that says that
when is the
directional derivative
at F the greatest?
>> Well, it's the greatest.
>> When the cosine of
theta is the greatest,
The cosine of theta
is the greatest at
one that occurs
when theta is 0.
>> Ok?
>> So the directional
derivative
is the greatest
when theta is 0.
But theta is the
angle between
the gradient of f
in the direction.
So that must mean
the direction
is the same as
the gradient.
So the gradient itself
is a vector that points in
the direction of when
the directional derivative
is the gradient.
So the gradient
is a vector that
points in the direction
of steepest, the,
the steepest part
of the graph or
the greatest dissent,
when is it least?
It's when the
cosine of theta
is equal to negative one.
So that's when
theta is equal
to 180 degrees or pi,
which is
the opposite direction
of the gradient.
And then when is
it equal to 0?
When is there no change in
the function happens to
be when theta is
equal to pi over two.
And that means that
the angle between
the gradient and
the direction
is 90 degrees
or pi over two.
So they are orthogonal.
So the gradient
vector points in
the direction orthogonal
to the level curves.
And the level curves being
the curve in which
you walk along
the surface of the
function where you are not
changing and it's
in the z value.
Okay? So all of this is
formalized in the
following theorem.
Let's take a look
at an example
where we can use some
of this information.
So we're given a function
and we're thinking of water
being poured on at a
particular point
on the surface.
Here at x is one
and y is 1 fourth.
What path does it tapers?
It flows downhill.
So we want to do is set
up where will this,
if we think of
a particle of
water starting
at the surface,
in which direction
should I go?
Well, I should
probably go in
the direction of
the steepest,
steepest descent, right?
So negative the
gradient vector,
the gradient vector points
in the direction of
steepest and the negative,
the gradient
vector points in
the opposite
direction where
it's the steepest downhill.
So the rate, right,
if we have the path of
water particle, the rate,
which is the derivative,
has to be in the direction
of the negative of
the gradient vector.
But we can find the
gradient factor
by taking the
partial derivatives
and we can just
set it equal.
Now, if two vectors
are parallel,
are pointing in the
same direction,
mathematically,
that means that
one vector is a constant
multiple of the other.
So in the set up here,
we're just going to say
there is some constant C.
Don't necessarily
know what it is yet,
but the negative
of the gradient
is some constant times the,
the rate of change of
this water particle.
So you can take the
partial derivatives,
stick those into
this equation.
And that gives us two
equations involving
x and x prime and
y and y prime.
So it can you
solve for c and
set those equal
to each other?
That gives us
the following.
And then since
we're dividing by
a small change in
T and both sides,
that allows us to
write the equation
without D
t. Then we can
integrate both sides.
That gives us the
following antiderivatives.
Then multiply it times
both sides times four,
because there's
a new constant
of integration.
Notice that we get a
constant of integration
from both sides,
but we can kind of
combine that into
one new constant
integration.
C1 then multiply
both sides times
four gives us a new
constant, iteration C2.
Use some properties
of logarithms here.
Raise both sides to
the E power to remove
the natural logs.
And we can use
the properties of
an exponential.
Notice that e to a
constant is just a
constant itself.
And that gives
us the following
equation in the x,
y axis,
which the direction of
the water must flow.
Now we have this new
constant c For we
know that we're going
to start at the
0.1 comma 1 fourth.
So we can put
that in for x and
y and solve for C four.
And that gives us the curve
which the path the
water will follow.
Ok? So if we
parameterize that curve,
we get t comma
14 t squared.
And if you graph the level
curves of the function,
we can see in
this animation here that
that parametrization
does indeed always find
itself perpendicular
to the level curves
of the function.
Which means as
it travels down,
it really is going down
the steepest path.
And this animation
on the right,
we're just graphing the
same, the same curve,
but in
three-dimensional space
with the corresponding
z value.
You can see if
a water droplet
was started here.
>> It's going to
follow the path is
indicated more on
the gradient vector.
>> Given a function
of three variables,
we can also find its
gradient vector,
which is the vector of
partial derivatives
with respect to
each variable.
And again, the
directional derivative is
the same formula where
you're taking
the dot product,
the gradient, with
its direction.
In this case, in
three-dimensional space.
In R3, the direction vector
has three components.
And this is just
a summary of what
we've already discussed for
functions of two variables.
But it's also true
for functions of
three variables that we can
find the maximum value
of the function.
It's the magnitude
of the gradient.
The direction of
the maximum value
is the direction of
the gradient itself.
The minimum value
is negative.
The gradient and
the director or
the I'm sorry,
the minimum value
is negative
the magnitude of
the gradient,
the direction is
negative the gradient.
And then when
the gradient is
orthogonal to the direction
is when there is no
change in the function.