Let's take a look at lines
in three-dimensional space.
>> This is an
overview of section
10.5 and our text.
>> The best way to
understand lines in
three-dimensional
space is to re,
understand lines in
two-dimensional space.
>> This is a familiar
equation here.
>> Y is equal
to negative two
thirds x plus four.
>> The graph of the
line is given here.
>> And the main thing
to remember is that
this equation gives us
two pieces of information
about the line.
>> It gives us
a slope, which
we can interpret as a
direction of the line.
>> And it gives us a point,
which is some
point on the line,
in this case, 0 comma four,
which is the y-intercept.
>> We can reinterpret
that information
as a direction vector.
Remember, the slope
is the change
in y over the change of x.
So we can put that
information into
a vector D as three
comma negative two.
And that gives us
the green arrow
that you see here.
And then we have a
starting position,
which we see as
the blue arrow.
And that allows us to
write an equation of
a vector that changes
as t moves t as a
parameter, a real number.
And as t increases,
they starting vector,
the blue arrow, changes
in the direction of
the direction vector.
Now this is a new
kind of function.
>> This is a function
whose output is
not a real number,
but whose output
is a vector.
>> This is the vector
equation of the line.
So this gives rise to
three new types of
equations for a line.
>> So we have a
vector equation,
which we just saw.
>> And if the
vector equation
describes a
vector x comma y,
then we can equate
the components.
>> Here.
>> X is equal to 0 plus 3t,
which tells us
the exposition.
>> For any value of
the parameter t,
y is equal to
four minus 2T,
which tells us the y
position for
every parameter
t. These two equations
together are called the
parametric equations
of a line.
>> As t varies,
it describes a different x
comma y point on the line.
>> In both of these,
you can solve for
t. And since t is
the same bolt,
set those equal
to each other.
>> And that gives us
the symmetric equation
for the line.
So this gives us
three new equations
for the line.
>> All of them give
us this important
information.
>> One of them
is the original
position on the line,
in this case, 0 comma four.
>> And all of them,
all of them give us
the direction which we
normally think
of as the slope.
>> In the symmetric
equations,
you can solve for y.
>> And you actually,
you get up, you
get exactly what
we started with.
>> Minds in
three-dimensions
are pretty much the same,
except we have
three coordinates.
>> You have a
starting, starting
position and you have
a direction vector.
>> If you equate the
three components,
you get the three
parametric equations.
>> And if you solve for t
in the parametric equations
and then set those
equal to each other,
you get the
symmetric equations
Important thing to remember
is all of them have
a position and a direction.
>> Let's find the
parameter equations
of a line through
the points two
negative 12 and the
0.13 negative one.
I'm gonna take an
initial position
vector as two,
negative 12 as given.
>> And then for
a direction,
I'll just take the
vector from P to Q.
We can find that
vector to be
negative 14,
negative three.
I always like once we have
the starting vector
and a direction,
I always write down
the vector equation
just because it's
handy to have.
>> It has the starting
position and then
the direction
vector right there,
where we can skip straight
to the parametric
equations,
which are written
like this,
with the starting
position values
x-naught, y-naught,
z naught.
>> And this started in the
direction vector
components a, B, and C.
>> So there we have
the parametric
equations for this line.
Lines in three-dimensional
space can
be situated in any
of these four ways.
>> They can intersect at 1,
they can intersect
at all points,
which means that
the same line,
they can point in
the same direction
but not intersect.
And that means the two
lines are parallel
or they can
non-intersecting
point in different
directions,
which means the two
lines are skew.
>> Consider the two lines
given here and parametric
equations determine
whether the
same they are the same
line they intersect,
are parallel or skew.
To determine if the
lines are parallel,
we just have to
compare the
direction vectors.
>> And the direction
vectors are given as
the coefficients
in front of
the parameter t and
s respectively.
>> So the direction vector
of the line one is three,
negative 11, and the
direction vector
of line two is 412.
>> If we can see that
these two vectors are
not parallel sends,
one can be written as
a constant multiple
of the other just
by looking at,
because the numbers
are kinda nice.
But in general, the
numbers may not be nice.
It may be hard to tell if
one vector can
be written as
a constant multiple
of the other.
>> So the procedure
is to set
one vector equal to
a constant times the other.
>> That gives you,
in this case,
three separate equations
with C involved.
>> But this shows
that C is equal to
three fourths and c is
equal to negative one,
which can't both be true.
>> So there is no such.
>> See the vectors are not
constant multiples
of each other
and they are not parallel.
Since the lines
aren't parallel,
they must be either
intersecting or
skew to determine if
they're intersecting.
>> We notice
that if there is
a point where they
both have in common,
then there must
be a value for
t and there must be a value
for S that have
the same x value,
the same y value, and
the same z value.
>> So if we set the
three equations
equal to, equal
to each other,
that just gives us a system
of linear equations
to solve,
very much like our
previous algebra class.
>> What I did here is I
just added the second,
third equations
to eliminate
the T. And it turns
out that as has to be
negative two and
t has to be one.
But if you put
that back into
the top equation, you
get a contradiction.
>> So that means these
two lines do not
intersect, so it
must be skew.
>> Something else we
need to be able to
do is to find the
distance from a point
to a line given a point
q not on the line,
in some line with
position p in
direction vector D.
>> You have a picture that
looks kinda like this.
In a handy way to remember
this formula is to remember
that the magnitude of
the cross-product is
the area of the
parallelogram.
So if you take a look
at this picture,
we have a vector PQ and
we have a vector d,
the direction
vector on the line.
What we really want
is the distance
from point q to the line.
That's the height of
the parallelogram that
you get when you are
that's formed by pq and
D. So we can
find the area of
the parallelogram by taking
the cross product
and divide
by the base to
get the height.
>> So it's really just area
equals base times height.
>> But in this
case we're solving
for the height of
the parallelogram.
>> And that's a handy way
to remember this formula.
>> The distance
between two lines,
if the two lines intersect,
the distance is 0.
If the two lines
are parallel,
you could just
take a point on
one of the lines
and then use
the previous slide to find
the distance from that
point to the other line.
>> Now the situation's
more interesting.
>> If you have
to skew lines.
If you have to skew lines,
what you do is you
take a point on
each line and then you
take the projection
of that vector form
from 1 to the other
on to a vector that's in
the direction
that's orthogonal
to both of the lines.
>> It takes a little
bit of thinking to
convince yourself that
that actually works.
But the shortest
distance between
these two skew
lines is exactly
the place where the vector
that's orthogonal
to both directions.
>> So we can find
the vector that's
orthogonal to both
directions by
finding the directions of
both lines, D1 and D2.
>> Taking the
cross-product gives us C.
>> And then you can
use this formula
here to calculate
the distance.
>> So let's find the
distance between
the two lines
that we looked
at in the previous example.
>> First thing
you need to do
to find the
distance between
two lines is determine
what kind of
lines are they?
>> Are they intersecting
or are they parallel?
>> In this case,
we already found
these two lines to be skew.
So we have to
use the formula
for the distance
between skew lines.
>> So first we identify
a point on each line,
and then we identify that
the direction vectors of
each line, which
can be found here.
A point on the first
line is one to 0.
On the second line
is negative 235.
>> The direction vector of
the first line is three,
negative 11, and the
direction vector
of the second line is 412.
>> Then we can find
the vector P1, P2.
We can find the vector C,
which is the cross-product
of D1 and D2.
>> It's good
practice for finding
cross-products,
the two vectors.
>> The dot
product of P1, P2
with C gives us 42,
the magnitude of
the vector c,
because a squared
is 62, and
therefore the
distance between
these two skew lines is
42 divided by the
square root of 62.