Let's take a look at
line integrals over
vector fields.
In section 14.3.
We'll start by looking at
work in vector fields as
a motivation for the model
of line integrals
in vector fields.
If we have a vector field
and a curve inside of it,
it's natural to
think about how much
work is the vector field
doing for a particle to
move along that curve?
Strategy is to take
a look a small
piece along the curve
that's going to be
the distance and
the direction
with the unit tangent
t. Unit tangent T.
And then remember that work
is the dot product of
the force applied with
the direction that
the work is done.
So the direction
the work is
done here is the
unit tangent T,
and the distance
is delta s. And
the force being
applied to at
any particular point comes
from the vector field.
So to find the
work, we find
the work in each smaller
and smaller piece.
And then we sum
that all up with
a, an integral.
And since the work
is being done
over the curve C,
we're going to
integrate over c. Okay?
Then if we have a
parametrization
of the curve r,
we can find these two
values in terms of
the parametrization
and update
our, our work integral.
And we see that
the work integral
really is just the line
integral of the vector
field over the curve.
So this gives us a
handy way to find
work of a line integral
in a vector field.
We just parameterize
the curve,
put the curve into the
vector field function,
find the derivative of
the parameterization and
calculate the
corresponding integral.
For properties
of, properties
of line integrals
over vector fields.
The first two are
very, very familiar.
We can pull out constants
and some the functions.
The last one
says that if we
parameterize
the curve in a,
in a vector field and
find its work integral,
It's going to be the
opposite or the negative
of if we parameterize
it the other way.
So let's look at
this vector field
defined capital F here.
And the path c
that starts at
the origin goes along
the blue curve to
the 0.1 comma one,
and then goes back
to the origin
along a straight line.
And we want to find what's
the total work
that's done by
the vector field
as a particle
moves along that path.
Since the path,
which we'll call c1,
the blue NC2,
do not have a
smooth connection.
Here we have to separate
the curve c into two
pieces, c1 and c2.
We can parameterize
C1 and C2.
So C1 is just
parameterized by t,
t cubed as t goes
from 0 to one,
and c2 is
parameterized by t,
t. Note that the
parametrization for c2
here that we've given
actually starts
at 0 comma 0,
and then moves to
one comma one.
So it's going in the
opposite direction
that we want C2 to move in.
That's okay, because
all we have to
do is negate the
line integral.
And that will give us
the orientation
that we want.
So this gives
us some freedom
to define a sort of
easier parameterization
and then
allows us to just flip
the orientation by
negating the integral.
The total work being
done over the
entire curve is
just the difference here of
the line integral of the
vector field over c,
one minus of the
vector field over C2.
So we do is we put our
parameterizations,
R1 into f and R2 into
f. Here we take
the derivative of
the parameterizations
that gives
us a dot product
of two vectors in
terms of the
variable t. And we
get some nice polynomial
functions to integrate.
And we get that
the total work
is negative three-fourths.
To do more with
line integrals,
we need to understand
a little bit more of the,
how sets are, are built in
different properties
or different kinds of
sets in two
dimensional space.
In three-dimensional space,
we can see that
what we mean by
connected is that a
connected set is that any
two points that we can find
a path from one to the
other that stays
inside the set.
We can see that for the two
dimensional example
here on the left,
these, this set
is not connected.
You can get from
the left piece to
the right piece.
Same with a2 surfaces
here in
three-dimensional space,
the two in the middle are
connected from any point
to any other point,
we can find a
path that remains
inside the set.
The same with the
doughnut here,
often called the tourists.
But they can, if
you can't retract
the path without passing
through a part that
is not in the set.
So if you think of
it like a string,
if you start at a point
and you loop back,
you can create
a loop where if
you try to deform that
string to a point,
that loop would pass
through parts of
the past to things that
are not in the set.
So this is just a
way of describing
holes in some
sense an estimate.
It's not simply connected.
The donuts not simply
connected because any,
any loop that goes along
these holes around
the outside
can't be retracted without
passing through the hole.
And then we see two simply
connected sets
on the right,
the just plain region here.
And then we have
a globe with
our piece missing
on the inside.
Any loop inside can be
deformed to appoint,
even, even with the
hollow part missing.
If we have a vector field
who comes from a
potential function,
which we'll describe
in a minute.
We call conservative.
And this is the
definition of
a conservative
vector field.
A conservative
vector field is
a vector field
where if you have
any path in
the vector field
between two points,
that the work
integral remains the
same no matter what
path that you choose.
So you start at point a,
you end at point
B in you go
from point a to point
B along one path,
you calculate the end,
the work integral
and you get a value.
And it's a conservative
vector field
if any other path
gives you that
exact same value.
This property is called
path independence,
and it's pretty
important in physics.
There's an important
theorem that says that
the work integral census
path independent.
If we have a function
whose gradient is
the vector field,
that grid, that,
that function is called
a potential function,
actually acts like
an antiderivative
in the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
So the work integral
is very easy to calculate.
You find the
potential function
whose gradient is
the vector field.
And then just evaluate at
the two points and
take the difference.
Let's take a look
at an example.
So here we have the
following vector field
and points a and B.
We want to show that
this vector fields
a conservative
vector field.
And then we'll
calculate the
work from a to B,
Hopefully easily using
path independence
to show that it's
a conservative
vector field.
We're trying to
find a function
whose gradient is F.
So we're trying to
find a function
whose partial derivative
with respect to
x is 3x squared y plus 2x.
And whose partial
derivative with respect to
y is x cubed plus one.
So we can do is integrate
the left hand function
here with respect to x,
integrate the right hand
function with respect to y.
And that will
produce hopefully
a function whose derivative
with respect to x is this
on the left and
whose derivative is
like the wisest
one on the right.
So we go through
that process.
But remember when we
integrate with
respect to x,
the constant of integration
could be any function of y,
because when we take
the derivative
with respect to x,
y is considered a constant.
So you integrate
with respect to x,
you integrate with
respect to y,
and we get these two
constants of integration.
But we know that
these two functions
must be the same.
So by saying them equal,
that gives us a clear
choice for what to
choose for the constant
of integration with
respect to y and
the constant
integration of x here.
If we choose the
constant mitigation
director y to just be Y,
then that will match up
with the right hand side.
If we choose the
constant here with
wrecked acts,
make it be x squared,
it'll matter.
But the left hand
side, and that gives
us a function with the
desired properties.
So that's a
potential function
for the vector field.
We've engineered it, so
its gradient is
the vector field.
We know that path
independence
holds based on the
previous theorem.
So if we want to
find the work
done from point
a to point B,
we simply evaluate
the end points,
in this case 011, for
at the end points of
our potential function.
To find the work done
much easier than
parameterizing
the curve and
using the formulas
we saw earlier.
Another way to test
whether a vector field is
a conservative
field is that
its curl is 0
throughout the field.