Let's take a look at
double integration with
polar coordinates.
>> Doesn't overview
of Section 13.3.
>> To talk about
double integrals
in polar coordinates,
we need to construct
the integral,
the double integral, in
terms of polar
coordinate regions.
>> In order to do that,
we need to understand
what is the area of
a rect and for
rectangular region
subdivided into
polar rectangles.
Now polar rectangle
is a rectangle that's
bounded by two
different R values
and two different
theta values.
We can try to
find the area of
one of these pieces
by just using
some basic geometry where
we have the proportion of
all the way around
the circle,
which is the delta theta is
the angle here
divided by two pi.
>> So that's the
proportion of the circle.
>> And then we have the
circle with the radius R2,
R2, R2 squared pi,
and then the circle with
the smaller radius,
R1 squared pi,
the area that actually
this formula
describes the area
of this piece
of the sector.
Now we can simplify a
bit, cancel the pies,
and then write
the difference
of squares and factor it.
>> And what we see
is when we let
R one and R2
become very close,
and we let delta
theta becomes 0.
>> We can use some
notation here to write
delta r is the difference
between R1 and R2.
And then R1 plus
R2 over two is
just the average of
these two values.
So we get a
convenient formula
for how the change of
the area of one of
these little
rectangles behaves
as our changes and
delta changes,
I'm sorry, theta changes.
So now we're going to
take the limit and
then we actually get
this convenient formula for
the differentials that tell
us how to approximate
change in area for
small nudges in the
radius and the angle.
Note here that how to,
when we write the
iterated integral,
it's not just the
function with x
and y replaced with r
cosine theta, r sine theta.
But we also have
an r d r d theta.
So let's use this technique
to find the volume
underneath the plane
over the unit disk.
So in this plane,
I'm sorry,
in this example,
we're going to
find the volume
over the unit disc.
And the unit disk is
just defined as the,
the points where
x squared plus
y squared is less
than or equal to one.
And then we can write
the double integral in
its general form of
the function that describes
the plane over
the region R.
Now to write it as an
integral in polar
coordinates,
we want to make
the appropriate
substitutions where x is r,
cosine theta y is r,
sine theta r goes
from 0 to one and
the unit disc.
And then we're going all
the way around the circle.
Theta goes from
0 to two pi.
Now we have an
iterated integral,
two variables and we
can compute it like usual.
So here we fact we
multiply through by r,
find the derivative
with respect
the antiderivative
to r of the inside,
evaluate at the end points.
And now we just
have a regular
integral with
respect to theta.
And we get our
answer is four pi.
>> And what are
we finding here?
>> We are finding the
volume underneath
the surface of the plane
above the unit disk.
So it's this piece
underneath the plane here.