Let's talk a
little Cartesian
coordinates in 3D space.
This is an overview
of section
10.1 from our book,
Cartesian coordinates
in 3D space,
or a way of describing
the location of a point
in 3D space with
respect to some origin.
The origin is
usually denoted
0 comma 0, comma 0.
It's very similar
to the way
you describe points
in 2D space,
except we have an
extra coordinate.
The 0.2 comma
three comma five
is two units in
the X direction,
three units in the Y, and
five units in
the z-direction.
And we can have lots of
points and we can have
equations that
describe many points.
We can also talk about
distance in 3D space.
If you have two points,
the distance between them
is given by this formula,
which is the square
root of the sum of
the squares of
the differences
of the respective
coordinates.
It's very similar to
the distance formula
in two dimensions.
In fact, it's just
another application
of the Pythagorean theorem.
Here I show that we
have two points,
1-2-3, 4-5-6.
How can you, how do
you find the distance?
You put them
into the formula
and calculate like this.
And a natural object
in three-dimensional
space as a sphere,
which is the set
of points that are
all the same distance
from some point
called a center.
If you have the
center being
abc and a radius being r,
then you can describe
the distance from
the point XYZ to the
point a BC equal to r.
>> That's the
distance formula.
>> And if you
square both sides,
you get exactly this
standard equation
of the sphere.
Oftentimes,
you're given an
equation that doesn't
look exactly like
a sphere per se.
But if you group the x, y,
and z terms together,
like we did in
this example,
you can see that
you can complete
the square and
then gather the x,
y, and z squared's.
And then it is
just a sphere.
And this sphere
is centered at
negative one comma two,
comma three, With
radius four.
We can also have planes
in three-dimensional space.
Here we have three
coordinate planes,
and these are
the most common.
The XY plane,
which is the set
of points with
a Z value of 0.
The YZ plane, which is
the set of points
with an x value of 0.
And the X Z plane,
which is a set of points.
What the y value of 0.
These planes help
us describe what's
happening in these
three cross-sections.
So no matter what kind
of graph we have,
no matter what kind of
function that we're given,
we often like to simplify
the situation by
looking at what's
happening in one of
these three
coordinate planes.
Because then the
three-dimensional graph
just becomes a
two-dimensional graph.
And we can use all
the results that we
know from one-dimensional
calculus.
So the equations
for these planes
are z equals to 0,
x equals to 0, and
y equals to 0 respectively.
A cylinder in
three-dimensional space
is a bit more general
than what we usually
think of as a cylinder.
A cylinder we
usually think of
as sort of like a tin can,
like we see here in the
picture on the bottom left.
In calculus, a cylinder is
A set of parallel lines
grouped together.
>> Essentially, these
are called the rulings.
And we can see that
the picture on
the bottom right,
If you have a curve
like a parabola there,
and then you have
all of the lines
that go through
that parabola.
>> And that surface
that's formed by
all those lines
is a cylinder.
So it's the cylinder
is the surface that you get
by connecting together all
of these parallel lines.
We also describe
the many services in
three-dimensional space
by revolving
other surfaces that
we already know.
So in this case,
we have y equals
the sine of z.
So if you kind of tilt
your head and you
can see that our z
as the independent
variable,
we just have a
normal sine function
there from 0 to pi.
And in the y z plane,
that is what it looks like.
Y equals the sine of z.
And you can rotate that
around the z-axis.
And then you get
nice, you get
this nice TOP
looking surface.
Some important kinds of
surfaces are
quadratic surfaces.
A quadric services are
an extension of the idea of
conic sections from
precalculus and calculus.
And if you see
the equation here for
a quadratic surface,
it's very similar to
the general equation of
a conic section when
we sketch quadratic
surfaces,
we have modern software
that helps us quite a bit
these days, but oftentimes,
a simple sketch on
your own can help you
solve a seemingly
intractable problem
in seconds.
Just by helping you
simplify the situation,
by understanding what kind
of object we're
dealing with.
>> The typical way
that you sketch
a quarter x surface
or most surfaces is just to
sketch some cross sections.
>> So in a surface
like this,
if this is a hyperbola
or hyperboloid,
and the equation of
a hyperboloid
here is given.
And if you want to
graphic yourself,
what you could
do is just let
x be 0, let's say.
And if you put x
equals to 0 in,
what you're left
with is just a y
squared over b squared
minus z squared over
c squared equal one,
which is a hyperbola.
So when x is equal to 0,
remember that's
the y z plane.
So by setting x equal to 0,
you're looking
at the curve in
the YZ plane of that
part of the surface.
So this is taking
cross sections
of the surface in
a systematic way.
And if the years,
if your graph is
centered at the origin,
which this one is,
the typical cross
sections to
take would be the
coordinate axes,
x equal to 0, y equal
to 0, and z equal to 0