Hello. Let's take a look at
the calculus of motion.
This is an overview
of Section
11.3 when you talk
about velocity, speed
and acceleration.
We've already been
using this language
in the previous video,
but if we think of
our vector valued
function r as position,
then its derivative
is given by
velocity or
the instantaneous
rate of the position.
The magnitude
of the velocity
is what we think
of as speed.
Andy, acceleration is
the second derivative.
Here's an example
where we have
a young boy whirling
a ball attached to
a string above his head
in a counterclockwise way.
In this example, the,
it's making one revolution
every two pi seconds.
>> And this string has
a length of two feet.
So you should notice
immediately that this is
pretty much impossible
on our planet.
>> Two pi seconds
is too long
for us to go
around for with a
length of two feet.
But it makes the math
easier for this problem.
And so the math
will be the same
if the rotated faster.
It would just change
the equations a little bit.
>> But let's play
along. First, let's
find the position
vector that
describes a situation
while the ball
is spinning around
counterclockwise.
>> So that's given
by the vector
valued function cosine t,
sine t, but the
radius is two,
so we multiply two
in each component.
Then the velocity
of the ball then
is the derivative
of that position.
So you take the derivative
of each component
and you get the
velocity vector.
>> And then the
acceleration
is the derivative
of the velocity.
>> So again,
simple derivatives
taken in each component.
The acceleration
is the rate at
which the velocity
is changing.
It helps to understand
acceleration by looking at
a plot of the
acceleration vector.
>> So as T stands for time
moves from t equals
to 0 and increases,
we can see what happens to
the position
vector in blue,
the velocity vector in red,
and then the acceleration
vector in green.
>> Immediately, we
can already see
the acceleration vector is
pointing back away
from the circle.
So maybe it's
not surprising
that the acceleration
as you traverse
around a circle is
always constant
inwards towards
the middle to determine
the point at which the
released the ball.
So they hits a tree.
That was question number
three in the
original problem.
>> The tree stands
ten feet in front
of the boy.
>> Value of t
should the boy
released the string so
the ball hits the tree.
>> We can model
the situation
with a circle with the ball
spinning around
and then putting
a point at 0 comma ten
dedicate the tree.
>> So mathematically, what
we're really trying to do
is find the tangent line.
Whereas the ball is at
any point around
the circle,
the tangent line that goes
through the 0 comma ten.
So we can write
the equation of
the tangent line where
t naught is the time that
we will release the ball.
>> And that gives us
these two equations.
These two equations give us
parametric equations
where we know that
if indeed the point
is 0 comma ten
is on the line,
then this will equal 0.
>> At some point,
the x value equals
0 and the y value
equal, equal ten.
No, I don't show
the details here,
but you can solve
both of these equations
simultaneously.
One way to do it here
is to solve for t.
>> In the top equation
software t and
the bottom equation set
those two equations
equal to each other,
and that eliminates
the variable t.
>> And then you just
solve for t sub 0,
which is a trig equation.
And when you do that,
you get sine inverse
of 1 fifth, which is 0.2.
>> And after graphing it,
we can see that
that's correct,
that when you put
0.2 into T sub 0,
that gives us
exactly the tangent
line that goes
through the point.
>> So that is the angle for
which the ball
should be released
to hitters hit the tree.
Vector-valued functions
allow us to talk about
project to
projectile motion.
And when we're on planet,
like a planet
Earth, for example,
you have a
gravitational constant,
which is a force
being pushed down.
>> And we can use the
gravitational constant
here to give the X and Y
coordinates of
position given
an initial speed and
an angle of elevation.
>> We also have
nice formulas
for the distance traveled.
>> We can talk about
the total distance traveled
by integrating the
velocity vector,
the magnitude of the
velocity vector.
Notice that's the
total distance
traveled over
that interval.
>> And we don't really know
the direction where we're
integrating the speed,
the magnitude of the
velocity vector.
>> Here we can find
the average speed by
taking the speed over
the interval and then
divided by the length of
the interval and
then the average velocity
in the same way.
Note that the average speed
doesn't give us
a direction.
>> And the average
speed here
is actually going to
be just a number.
The average velocity is
going to give us a vector.