Let's take a look at
vector fields in section
14 to a vector field
is a function.
And for every point in
a set in the plane,
R2 are in
three-dimensional space.
R3 is associated
with a vector,
usually a capital F
or a capital letter
is what we use to denote
the vector field function.
And the components of
the vector field function
are usually used with
the letters capital M,
capital N. But
the important
thing to remember
is that a vector field sort
of as a collection
of vectors,
but it's a collection
of vectors
that every point in
the domain is
associated with
a single vector.
Here's a picture of
a few vector fields.
The first one
here is a vector
field on the square
from negative one to
one in the plane.
The second one is a
vector field over
the whole plane.
And then the third is a
vector plane over all
of R3 in
three-dimensional space.
Each component of
a vector field is
a scalar or a real
valued function.
Oftentimes when
we're talking about
the vector field
as a whole,
we kinda drop the x
and y are the X, Y, and Z.
And we just write
the letters of the,
of the component functions.
An important
object for talking
about things that
our vector field
is the del operator.
That's this upside
down triangle here.
If we have, we've
already seen this
in context of the gradient.
So if we have a function,
the gradient was this
del of f equals to
the vector of partial
derivatives of
f. So in fact,
if we have a function
that's differentiable,
then the gradient
itself defines
a vector field
for every point
x comma y in the domain
of the function,
there is a
corresponding vector,
the gradient, and that
those vectors correspond
to a vector field.
But let's just focus
on the operator,
the triangle
operator itself.
We like to think of
that as being a vector,
any vector of
derivative operators.
Since F, when we looked
at the gradient,
f is a scalar function.
When you write
the del operator
as this vector
of derivatives,
you just follow the
normal laws of vectors.
We bring the F into
each component,
apply the operator to f,
and that's how you
get the partial
derivatives.
So this is just a new way
of looking at the gradient,
but with a focus
on the action
of this operator itself.
One of the
important ideas n
a vector field
is divergence,
which is a measure of how
the movement in
the vector field is
either compressing,
things, are
expanding things.
This is really useful
in fluid situations,
gas or liquids,
that you want
to know whether
there is expansion
happening or compression.
To measure the divergence,
it's convenient to
use the del operator,
and it's actually
defined as
just the dot product
of the del operator
with the vector field.
Also with a vector field,
a really important
idea is the curl,
which measures the spinning
action of the vector field.
Oftentimes we want to
know how are things are
rotating inside
the vector field.
And the del operator
is also convenient
to find the curl.
It's actually the
cross product
with the vector field.
So this gives a
convenient way to
remember the formula for
divergence and curl.
Let's take a look
at an example.
So here's a graph of
the vector field and
let's discuss its
divergence and curl.
The divergence is
the dot product
of the del operator
with the vector field.
So we take the doc
product, we apply it,
and we see that it's 0.
And what does that mean?
That means that
any point x comma
y in R vector field,
picture here, there is
no compression or expansion
happening at that point.
Things are not building
up the curl though,
since the, we see
things that are
kind of spinning
around in perhaps
consorting at places.
The curl does change from
place to place based
on this function,
cosine x plus sine of y.
If the vector field itself
can be found by taking
the gradient of a function,
then that function
is called
a potential function.
And that function plays
an important role
in some nice properties
of that particular
vector field.
Vector fields that have
a potential function
are often called the
conservative vector fields.
And how many broken
important properties
in physics.