Let's take a look at
a quick overview of
section 12.3 on
partial derivatives.
Partial derivatives of
a function of
two variables,
then the function
must be continuous,
are defined as the limit of
the difference
quotient, where the,
the limit is taken
as h goes to 0,
where h is added to
the X component before
the derivative with
respect to x and
the y component for the
derivative with
respect to Y.
If you're taking the
partial derivative
of a function of
two variables,
then it's partial
derivatives
are also functions
of two variables.
Let's take a look
at an example.
Here we're asked to
find the partial
derivative with
respect to x using
the limit definition.
But since we looked at
the definition and why
was acting as a constant,
we can take the
derivative of
this function
with respect to
x by thinking of
y as a constant.
So if y is a constant,
the derivative x
squared y is 2x y,
the derivative of
2x is just two.
And the derivative
of y cubed,
if y was acting
of the continent
would just be 0.
So that's the easy way
to find the partial
derivatives.
Now using the
limit definition,
we have to apply the
definition in the limit.
>> And then we put
an x plus h for
everywhere we see x for
the first part of
the expression.
>> Then we subtract
the function.
We need to expand all,
all that out,
gather our terms,
and some magic
happens where
everything that's left
over that doesn't
get cancelled
out has an H and the top,
the H on the top
cancels with h
on the bottom.
And then when you take
the limit as h goes to 0,
you are left with 2x,
2x y plus 2x,
which exactly the way that
we thought about it
in the first place.
Now we want to
interpret some
partial derivatives.
So find the partial
derivative with
respect to x
and y at the 0.2 comma one.
So first we find the
partial derivatives.
Then we put in the points.
Here we see the
partial with
respect to x is
negative three,
with respect to y is one.
What does the
negative three mean?
Well, it's the
instantaneous rate of
the function with respect
to the first variable.
That's one interpretation,
interpretation.
>> It's also the slope
or the steepness
of the function.
>> If you were to face in
the positive
x-direction and take
a one unit step forward.
So is talking about
how that function is
changing in the
positive x direction.
So in this case,
if you were to take
one step forward,
you would take
three steps down.
Sort of describes
the steepness
of the function in
that direction.
And similar for
the variable y.
So it's the slope of
the tangent line,
although we're talking
about a surface now,
it's the slope of
the tangent line
that's tangent in
that direction.
Here we see a couple
of pictures of
the tangent line in
the positive x direction
on the left and
the slope of the
tangent line in
the positive y
direction on the right,
we also have second
partial derivatives.
And if we take
the derivative respect
to x and then x again,
we use this del notation,
which was kind of
a funny-looking D.
And sometimes we write it
with the little acts
as a subscript.
The thing to notice with
the partial
derivative notation
here is that if
you're using
the, the fraction notation,
Leibniz's notation
sometimes called
the derivatives that work
from right to left
in terms of the order
in which you are
taking them.
So if we look at
number two here,
this function here,
we took the derivative
with respect to x,
then we took the derivative
with respect to y.
So when you see
this fraction
here was first x, then y.
But if you're going
to use the notation
on the right with
the subscripts.
It reads from
left to right,
first x, then y.
We want to be
able to interpret
second derivatives of
functions of two
variables in the same way
that we do it for
functions of one variable.
If you're looking in
only one direction,
the positive x direction.
And in fact, if
you just take
the cross section of
the graph in
that direction,
in the positive
x direction,
then you would
interpret the
second derivative
nearly the same as you
would in calculus one.
It's the rate at which
the slope is changing.
And it measures
the concavity in
that direction.
In the same thing for
the second derivative
with respect to y.
The mixed partial
derivatives R a little
bit more, more interesting.
So you want to
measure if you're
taking the derivative
with respect to
x and then y,
that's measuring how much
the function is
changing with
the function f of
x is changing with
respect to y as
x derivative with
respect to y.
The author in our book has
a really good analogy.
And I encourage you to
look at on page 706 on
the rolling
meadow functions
of three variables
are very similar.
It's the partial
derivative with respect
to any variable
x or y or z is
this limit of the
difference quotient where
the H is added to
the component in which
you're taking the
derivative of.
Interpretive
interpretations of
the derivative
are the same,
although the geometry is
slightly different
because the graph of
the function and here
is in four-dimensional
space.
But in terms of
rates of change in
that particular
direction than
the interpretations
are the same.