Let's look at a quick
overview of section
12.7 on tangent lines,
normal lines, and
tangent planes.
>> If we have
a curve in
three-dimensional space,
which is the graph of
a function of
two variables.
>> We can talk about
the tangent lines,
but there's tangent lines
in different directions.
You can have a tangent line
to the x direction,
y direction, and you can
add the tangent line
in any direction.
>> We've already talked
about the directional
derivative,
which tells us how
much the function is
changing in the
z direction.
>> And so for
the line, all we
need is a point.
And if we look at
numbers 123 year,
it's talking about the line
in the x direction,
y direction,
in any direction you,
but the point is the same.
>> X-naught,
y-naught, z naught,
which is what we get
when we put x nought,
y nought into the function.
>> And the
direction vector,
if we take a look
at the x direction,
is one step in the x
direction, one comma 0.
>> And then how,
how much do we
increase in the, in
the z direction?
Well,
that's the derivative
with respect to x,
similar in the y
direction, 0 comma one.
Then how much do
we increase in
the function with respect
to the y direction,
the derivative f
with respect to y.
>> And then similarly
in arbitrary direction U1,
U2 demanded,
demanded, the
function increases
the directional derivative.
>> So this is the
same equations
for lines that we
saw in chapter ten,
where we have a
point on the line
in a direction vector.
Except now the direction
vector is being
described in terms
of the derivative.
>> Here's an example to
find the tangent line.
>> So the surface of
this function
sine x cosine y.
>> And here it three
different directions.
>> The direction of x
drafted in direction of y,
and this direction,
negative 11.
>> We can remember that the
directional
derivative is defined
in terms of the
dot product of the
gradient with
the direction.
Here we're focusing
at the point
pi over two, pi over two.
>> And the x-direction
is an i, the i vector,
y directions, the j vector,
and the direction
of negative 11.
>> We have to scale it
by its magnitude to make
sure as length one
is the following.
To find the gradient,
we take the partial
derivatives
put in the point pi
over two, pi over two.
>> And here we just get 0
is the partial with
respect to x and
negative ones,
partial derivatives to y.
>> So in the x
direction we have
a point pi over
two comma pi over
two comma 0.
And then we have the
direction vector,
in this case, one comma 0.
>> And then the z
direction is 0.
So the equation of the
line is the following.
>> In the y direction, we
have our point
on the line Pi
over two comma pi
over two comma 0.
And the direction
vector here is
01, negative one.
And now with respect to
the other direction,
again,
wherever point and
wherever direction vector.
In our case,
the direction vector
is negative one over
root 21 over root two,
and then negative
one over root two.
Normal lines, normal lines
have been with
us all along,
we just haven't
looked at them that
closely and calculus one,
but we pay a lot
of attention
to the tangent line.
>> And in physics,
the normal lines are
important because it's
the direction of the
force opposite of,
of the, of the velocity,
or, I'm sorry, the
acceleration. On the graph
>> So if we have a
function of two variables
in a graph in
three-dimensional space,
what we can do is look at
the vectors that are
tangent to the plane,
which we've already seen
in previous slides.
>> So the direction,
the x direction and y
direction vectors are
given with these
two factors.
>> And to find a
normal vector,
we can take the
cross-product.
>> If we take the
cross-product to
actually get a
nice formula here.
It's the derivative with
respect to x, with
respect to y.
>> Come on one, these
two are negative.
>> Just for the sake of
having a nice formula,
usually take the
normal vector to
be the opposite direction,
which is still normal
to the tangent plane.
And we get a
nice formula for
the normal vector on
the surface of a function
of two variables.
>> It's sort of like
the gradient with
a negative one
attached at the end.
>> Now here's a problem
where we want to find
the distance from a
point to the surface.
So if you have a point q
sitting out in
space somewhere,
and we have a surface,
in this case,
two minus x squared,
minus y squared.
>> How can we find
that distance?
>> The mathematical
setup is to
find the any point on
the surface, call it P,
whose When you take
the vector PQ is
parallel to the
normal vector,
that will be the point
in which it will have
the shortest
distance. Okay?
>> So that's the
mathematical said we'll take
an arbitrary point P
at x-naught,
y-naught, z naught.
>> And find the vector
p to q and then
impose that that's parallel
to the normal vector.
So if we take our
point p here,
we, then we find
that the vector PQ,
we just take 2.2.2
and subtract the components
of P, The normal vector.
>> We use the formula
from the previous slide,
the partial derivatives
with respect to x,
y, and then negative
one at the end.
And then we impose that
these two vectors are
parallel because
that's where
the shortest
distance occurs.
And that gives us
three equations.
>> We can solve
for c in each of
these equations
and then set the
following equal
to each other.
And that gives us
the following.
>> Now, the first equation
here between x-naught
and why not?
You'll notice that
they are the same.
So this, this first
equation means that
x nought and y nought are
actually equal
to each other.
So if x dot is
equal to y naught,
then we can use
the other equation
defined what x-naught
might, might be.
So we want to solve for x
naught in the
following equation.
>> Now if we do some
rearranging here,
we get this cubic equation.
>> Four x cubed
plus x naught minus
two equals 0.
This is actually a
challenging equation
to find an exact answer.
It's not impossible,
but you can see you
some fun algebra to see
that you can get
the answer here.
Usually what we do in this
situation to
find the answer
is just a graph it and
find where it
crosses the x axis.
And in this case we
get about 0.68940.
>> Ok?
>> So that means we
find an x value,
our y-value, we
stick it into
the function to
find the z value.
And now we found a point on
the surface where it
has the shortest
distance to the point Q.
>> The actual distance
is the magnitude of
that vector from this
point P to the point Q.
The tangent plane is
actually been
lingering in the
background along.
We've had these
direction vectors
that are parallel to
the tangent plane.
And now we have a normal
vector at any point.
So a plane is
a point together with
the normal vector.
>> So a normal
vector is going to
be the partial derivative X
than Y negative one.
And those are
the coefficients
in front of each term.
>> And then the point
x nought, y nought,
and z nought,
the gradient.
>> You can find
the gradient of
a function of
three variables
in the same way.
And we can use
the fact that
the gradient vector is
always orthogonal to
the level curves.
>> This is actually
a very useful fact.
>> So if we have
a function of
three variables,
we can use the fact that
when we find the gradient,
it's orthogonal to
the level curves.
>> So here's an example.
Let's find the
normal vectors
on the surface of
this function.
And this is the
same function we
used in the
previous examples.
We can use the previous
theorem to realize
this function is actually
a level curve of
a function of one
more variable.
>> So if we let z
be f of x comma y,
and then move x0
to the other side.
>> Now we can see
that this surface
described by z equal to
two minus x squared minus
y squared is really
just this three-dimensional
function of x,
y, and z equal to 0.
>> So it's a level curve.
>> So defined
a level curve,
the vector that's
orthogonal
or normal to a level curve.
>> We take the gradient of
this three
variable function
and we can see that
we get negative 2x,
negative two, negative one,
which is exactly
what we got
before finding
the gradient by
using the normal vector
or the cross product
the other way.