Let's look at mass
and center of
mass and Section 13.4.
Sometimes we want to
describe something
called a lamina,
which is a planar
region here as
R with a constant
thickness and finite area.
We'll remember
from physics that
the mass of something
is its density
times its area.
Now if we take a small
piece of area here,
multiply it times
its density,
we will get that
small piece of mass.
And as we do that for tiny
little pieces
of the region,
add them all up,
and that can
approximate our total mass.
And then as we allow
those pieces to
get smaller and
smaller and smaller,
smaller, then we'll
defied the integral.
So to find the mass over
a planar region R with
the density function here.
Delta is our
density function
is just the double
integral of
the density function
over the region
R. So let's find
the mass of a square lamina
with variable density here.
Sometimes it's
convenient to
graph the lamina,
the planar region with
the density function.
And here we can
actually guess
what our answer
is going to be.
Because the density,
although it's different on
different parts
of the lamina,
we can see that
it's the same
as to the right
and to the left.
And it's going to be three
on average the route.
>> So the answer here
is going to be three,
and we can see that
just from the picture.
>> But we can
also set up the
integral of the density
function over the region.
And if we do that, so
we set up the double
integral over R of
the density function.
It's an iterated
integral first with
respect to x, then
with respect to y.
And we see that the
answer is indeed three,
and that is the
mass of the lamina.
You can also find
this center of mass.
So first of all,
look at centre of
mass of a discrete system.
And this is the
simplest kind
where we have masses
all a line and located
at various X values.
>> Notice the
notation here.
>> The center of
mass is x bar.
That's the same
as in statistics
where we use the average.
>> This is really just
the weighted average.
>> So now if we have
three masses here,
1021, located at
these x values,
we can find the center
of mass by looking at
the ratio of the product,
the sums of the products
of the masses with the x
coordinates all divided
by the total mass.
>> The top of the
expression here is
often what we call the
moment of the system.
>> And that's
helpful because
we're going to look at
masses located in
two dimensions.
We will have the
moment across about
the y-axis in a moment
about the x axis.
And that allows
us to define
the center of mass with,
with n masses
located in
two-dimensional space.
>> Note that here
the moment about
the y axis is just
summing up the,
the parts with the
x coordinates.
>> And the moment
about the x-axis is a
summing up the parts
with the y coordinates.
So this is a summary
of how we can
find the mass and
the center of
mass of an object in
two-dimensional space.
In this case, a
planar lamina.
The only difference
is now we
integrate instead of sum,
so it's find the center of
mass of a square lamina.
>> Similar as before,
except now we're try
before we found the mass.
>> Now let's find
the center of mass.
The mass we found
to be three.
The moment about
the x axis and
y axis are found with
the integrals here.
And so the center
of mass is
just the coordinates
of the following
expressions.