Let's take a
look at Section
14.1 on an introduction
to line integrals will
start with some notation.
When were first
introduced to
definite integrals of
a function with
one variable,
we often write the
limits of integration
on the bottom
and the top of
the integral
sign to indicate
that we can use
the fundamental
theorem of calculus.
That will be an
anti-derivative evaluated at
those two places and
then subtracted.
But when we're
talking about
integrals in general,
often the set that
we're integrating over,
in this case the D
interval from one to three.
Just write the letter that
corresponds to
that interval
underneath the
integral sign.
And we've already
seen this when we
first were setting up
double and triple
integrals.
Wherever it double
integral we're integrating
over a set in
the plane are,
and in triple integrals,
we're integrating
over a set of
points in
three-dimensional space.
When we're talking
about integrating
over more general sets,
we do the same
thing with we have
a symbol S that
corresponds to a set,
perhaps a curve in
three-dimensional space.
We will write
the set below,
the integral sign
and a function
defined on those set of
points we integrate.
And then d whatever,
where that whatever
is a symbol
that refers to
how we measure distance
or area or volume,
et cetera, in that set.
Now we are going
to look at a curve
C and try to
understand how we can
integrate a function
over a curve rather
than an interval.
The quiet is the same.
If we want to look at
the area underneath
the function,
above the curve, we chop
that curve into
tiny little pieces.
Each has a width, and then
the function corresponds
to a height.
And we add all of those,
those pieces up to get
an approximation
of the integral.
The nice thing
about intervals is
that it's really easy to
find distance in them.
Alright? The
interval from one to
three is three minus one.
And in general, the
interval from a to B
is the distance
or the length
of that integral
is b minus a.
So the math is very easy
to find distances in
intervals when we
have a curve though,
either curve in
the plane or
a curve in
three-dimensional space,
finding those
little bits of
pieces is a bit
more difficult.
And we have to
use arc length.
So the area under
the curve f
is approximated as
the sum all of these widths
and heights over
these small pieces.
And then we take
the pieces to
be smaller and
smaller and smaller,
which is indicated by this
double absolute
value sign here.
As those small arc length
gets minds smarter,
smaller, we ended up,
and that is what
we call the
integral over the curve
C of the function
S. So this is
the definition of the line
integral which we just saw.
And it's important to
understand that this
integral is defined in
this way as sort of
an approximation.
It's the limit of
these approximations
of the area under the,
under the curve f over D,
under the function
f over the curve C
Sometimes the curve
that we want to
integrate the function
over is closed,
meaning that it begins and
ends at the same point.
When that's the case,
we usually write
the integral sign with
this little circle in
it to indicate that
the curve that we're
enter integrating
over is closed.
For the rest of
the examples.
Here, we're going
to assume that
the curve is actually
in the x, y plane.
If we have a curve
in the x-y plane,
we can try to
find the arc length
parameter for the curve.
Parameterized the
parameterize the curve,
and then find the arc
length parameter.
Recall that the arc
length parameter
is defined as the
integral of the magnitude
of the derivative of
your parameterization
function,
where any
parameterization function
as it will work.
And then if we take
the derivative with
respect to t of both
sides of this equation,
we see that the, that
S prime is really
just the magnitude of
the derivative of
a prioritization.
So if we hit the
refresh button
on our integral here,
we can replace
as prime with
the magnitude of our
parameterization.
And that's what
we see here.
So we can, this will
allows us to get
a nice formula
for calculating
these line integrals.
And what we do is we
start with a
parametrization.
We can take its derivative,
find the magnitude
of that derivative,
and then we put the
parameterization pieces,
the X and Y pieces into
the function itself.
And then everything
is in terms
of the variable t
and reintegrate.
Let's look at an
example. Here we have
a surface defined
by the function
f over the x, y plane.
And we would like to know
the line integral
over the curve C,
where C here is described
as the line in
the xy plane,
Y equals 2X plus one,
where x goes between
negative 11.
So the goal is to
parameterize that curve.
And it's a straight line.
So we can parameterize
the curve
with T going from
negative one to one
and just use the function
with our parameter
t. We can take
the derivative and then
find the magnitude
of that vector.
Then we put our
values for x and
y t and two t
plus one in for x
and y to the function
we put an R prime
and then we just,
we have a simple integral.
So 14.418 is
the answer to this
line integral.
Remember what that
number means?
It actually corresponds to
the area below the
function and
above the curve.
Properties of line
integrals are thankfully
familiar to the properties
of other integrals
we've been looking at.
We can pull constants
out front and the Lyn,
It's separates
over addition.
We can break the curve into
pieces and then integrate
over those separate
pieces separately.