Here in Section 14.4,
we're going to take a
look at flow, flux,
Green's theorem
and the Divergence
Theorem. First, flow.
When the vector
fields interpreted
as velocity vectors.
Then the line integral over
a curve represents flow.
We've already looked
at line integrals in
a vector field that
we interpreted as
work previously.
If the vector field was a,
a bunch of forces.
Now we're thinking
of the vector field
as velocity vectors,
maybe describing how
things are moving.
So therefore, the
line integral now
represents the flow
over that curve.
Here we have a picture
of a vector field,
capital F and three curves.
If we look at the
flow of curve one,
we see that the flow of the
vector field is going
in the same direction
as the curve c1.
So therefore the flow is
going to be
positive over c1.
We're also going to learn
a notion called flux.
Flux is the measure of
the vector field crossing
the curve tangentially
or orthogonally.
We can see since
the flow is going
direly in the direction
of the curve c1,
the flux would
be 0 over C1.
The flow across C2
will be 0 because
the vector field
not contributing
any movement to movement
along the curve, C2.
But the flux would
be positive
because movement
across the curve is
entirely happening here.
And then in S3 is
a little bit of
both is happening fluxes,
the summation of the amount
of vector field
tangent to the curve.
So flow is the accumulation
of things going in
the direction of the curve,
flux or the things
crossing the curve.
We can define this
mathematically
with the two
integrals, right?
The flow is the movement
in the direction
of the curve
with a unit tangent vector.
The flux is the movement
tangent to the curve.
So use the normal
vector n. Now,
flux could be measured
in a couple of
different ways depending on
what you mean by
left to right or
right to left,
you can cross a curve
in two different ways.
So we have to define
what we mean by positive.
And we're talking
about a unit normal.
The unit normal
vector could be
like pointing to the
right of the curve,
but it could be
pointing to the left.
So defined this in general,
we have to be careful
about what is left,
what is right.
And in general,
the convention is
that if you have
a closed curve,
so like a loop that
comes back to itself,
the unit normal vector
points to the outside.
So remember that
the definition of
the unit tangent vector,
if we have a
parametrization of
our curve R is
given here as
capital T. Then
if we want to
rotate that 90
degrees to the right,
we're going to define
the outside of the curve is
always being to the right
as we traverse clockwise.
So by flipping
the components
of the x and y here
and negating it,
we have created a vector
that's orthogonal to
the unit tangent vector
and 90 degrees
to the right.
So that's what we'll
use as our unit normal
vector to define flux.
So flux is the integral of
the vector field dotted
with the normal vector.
And when we
substitute all values
in here and simplify,
we see that we start to get
a nice simple expression
for finding flux.
Now remember, m and n are
the component functions
of the vector field,
and f and g are
the components of the
parametrization
of the curve
C. Oftentimes we see
the flux written as
these bottom two integrals
because it's a
nice compact form.
But remember it
really is this line
integral dotted with
the unit normal vector.
So here we have
an example with
two curves, C1 and C2.
In a vector
field. We want to
find the flow in the flux
across the c1 and c2.
First, we parameterize c1.
We parameterize C1
starting when t is 0,
starts here at one comma 0.
And as t goes to one,
we end up at the
0 comma one.
So R, R1 parameterizes
the curve c1 in here.
C2 is actually a portion
of the unit circle.
So there we can
parameterize with cosine t,
sine t, as t goes from
0 to pi over two.
For the flow across C1,
we calculate the line
integral over the
vector field.
We put our parametrization
into the vector
field function,
and then we find
the derivative of
our parametrization.
You see here is
negative 11.
You take the dot
product and we get
a simple integral in our,
in our flow across
C1 is just one.
The flux across C1
is the'd dot product
with the normal vector.
Again, we use
the formula we
developed in the
previous slide,
where we have m times
the derivative of
g minus n times
the derivative of f. And
since we have these
component functions
for capital,
for the vector field m
here is negative x
and n is 2y minus x.
And we put in
our parametrization
into those values.
See the parameterization is
one minus t for x.
So we put in one minus
t everywhere we see an x,
we put a t everywhere
we see a y.
And that's where we see
these values come from.
But we see the flux
across C1 is actually 0.
And we can see in
the picture here
that makes sense
because we have things
crossing the
bottom part of C,
one from top to bottom,
but then they
are going back
across on the other side.
So the total accumulated
crossing here is 0.
Now we find the
flow for C2.
Again, we take our
parametrization,
we put it into
the vector field function
to find the derivative.
Take the dot product,
and then we have
a nice integral in here.
The flow is about 0.7.
And then finally,
the flux across C2.
Again, we put our
parametrization into
the vector field
function to get
function in terms
of t. And we
take the derivative of
the functions of our
parametrization,
make the
calculation, and we
get the flux being
about 0.285.
Green's theorem is
a very important fit
theorem that kind
of connects the work
integral with the curl
of the function
inside of the region.
So here's an example
of a vector field
over this region are
defined by a fairly
complicated
parameterized curve.
Now we're supposed to find
the circulation
around the curve
C. That would mean
parameterizing
this curve and,
and developing
the line integral
and integrating
these functions.
Instead, we can use greens,
Greens theorem to
find the curl of
the vector field
and then just
integrate that
over the region.
But it turns out
that the curl of
the vector field
is always 0.
So even though the region
inside of the curve is
somewhat complicated,
we can keep our integral
general and just
call that region R.
And we're just
going to integrate
the function 0 anyways,
so it's going to
be 0, so there is
no circulation
around the outside.
Another important
theorem is
the Debye
divergence theorem.
And this connects
the flux across
the boundary of
the region with
the divergence on the
inside of the region.
The benefit here
is that the line
integral can be somewhat
difficult integral to find.
So instead, maybe we
find the divergence
of the vector field,
which could be
quite simple,
and then find that
double integral instead.
So that's what's
happening here.
In this example, we
have a vector field
defined as capital F. Here,
curve is the circle
of radius two.
So we want to find the
flux across the curve.
Remember, that's,
that's the amount
of crossing
across the curve.
So we do this the hard way.
We would have to
actually parameterize
the curve and then
use the formula for
the, for the flux.
Instead, we can find
the divergence of
the vector field,
which we remember as
this formula here.
It's the derivative of the
first component
with respect to x
plus the second component
respect to y is just two.
So all we need to do
is find the double
integral over the inside of
the region of the
Function two.
And we get that I
simply eight pi