Let's take a look at planes
in three-dimensional space.
>> This is an
overview of section
10.6 from her book.
A plane in
three-dimensional
space is thought of
as an infinitely
large 2-dimensional
flat sheet.
>> Every plane has
what's called
normal vectors.
>> It's represented
by the nail
that you see in
the picture here.
>> Normal vectors
are vectors that
are orthogonal
to the plane.
>> The plane itself
is a collection
of points q,
in this case, such
that the vector
PQ is orthogonal to
this normal vector.
>> So if you have
a normal vector
and a point p,
then the plane
is all points Q,
such that the
dot product of
PQ with the normal
vector is equal to 0.
>> So if we have
a point P with
coordinates x-naught,
y-naught, Z naught, and X.
>> And Q has
coordinates x, y, z.
And the normal vector
has components ABC.
>> Then we can take
that equation expanded
out and will imply
the dot product.
>> And that gives us
this formula right here,
which is the standard
form of a plane.
>> The thing to take
away here is that
the normal vector is
right in the equation
of the plane a, B, C.
>> They are the
coefficients
that in front of x,
y, and z respectively.
>> And a point on the plane
we can see is x-naught,
y-naught, and Z naught.
If you substitute
x naught for x,
y naught for y z,
not z, you get 0 plus
0 plus 0, which is 0.
>> You can expand
this out in
distribute a and b and
c across the terms.
And then a and b
and c are numbers.
And so our x, y,
x naught, y naught,
and z naught.
>> Gather all
those together,
put them on the other side,
and call that D. That gives
us another form
of the plane.
>> An example, write
the equation of the plane
that passes through
the points 11012,
negative 1012.
>> The strategy here is
to use the three points,
define two vectors that
are parallel
with the plane,
then define the
normal vector.
>> We just take
the cross-product of
those two vectors.
I found that, I found
the vectors PQ and PR.
Those are two
vectors that are
parallel with the plane.
If you take the
cross product of
those two, I got 211.
>> And then a point
on the plane is 110.
>> Now we have
a normal vector
and a point on the plane.
>> So we can just
put that into
the standard form
for a plane.
>> And then we have our
equation for a plane.
>> Give the
parametric equations
of a line that is
the intersection
of the two planes
that you see here.
>> The strategy is to find
a direction vector for
the line of intersection.
>> So we could start
by adding and subtracting
the equations to each other
and trying to
eliminate variables.
>> But it's really
handy to notice
that the direction
vector of
the intersection line has
to be orthogonal to
the first plane,
and it has to be
orthogonal to the
section plane,
the second plane.
So it has to be
orthogonal to both.
>> And since both
planes give us
the normal vectors,
and in this case,
the normal vector of
plane one is one,
negative 11, and
the normal vector
of 0.2 is negative 211.
We can take the
cross product,
which is negative
two, negative three,
negative one, to find the
direction vector
to the plane.
>> So it's common if
you take the cross
product and you
find a possible direction
vector for the plane,
for, I'm sorry, for
the intersection line.
>> You can scale it
however you wish to find
another direction
vector that's
parallel or the same line.
>> So if in this case,
all three were negative by
multiplying times
negative one,
that changes
the orientation
of the direction vector,
but it's still the same
direction as the line.
So I'm taking the
direction vector to be
231 because the
numbers are nicer.
>> The same thing
can be done if
you had some
messy fractions
and you wanted
to just scale it
by a least common multiple,
and that would remove
all the fractions.
>> Now we just need to find
a point on the line.
>> Here.
>> I subtracted
the two equations
to eliminate Z,
and I was left with
3x minus two, i minus one.
>> Since there are
three variables
and two equations,
we're free to let
one variable,
the free I chose
x equals to 0,
that gives us y is
equal to negative one.
And we substitute,
substitute
those into the
first equation.
I get z is equal to
negative three halves.
>> So a point in
both of the planes
that I found was 0,
negative 1.5, and
negative three-halves.
>> We have a point
on the plane.
>> We have the
direction vector
that we found previously.
>> So we can put that into
the parametric
equations of a plane,
which of parity
equations for a line.
>> And that gives
us the equation
for the intersection line.
Something else
we'll need to
do is be able to find
the distance from a
point to a plane.
>> Here, if you take a
look at the picture,
if we have a point
q not on a plane,
we can find the distance
h to the plane,
which is the shortest
distance to the plane.
>> And notice that that
shortest distance is
in the same direction as
the normal vector
for the plane.
>> So if we take any
point on the plane,
in this case p,
form the vector PQ.
>> Then take the
vector projection of
PQ onto the normal vector
that's going to give
us a vector that has
the same length as
the height that we're
trying to find.
>> And so that's
the formula for
the distance from a
point to a plane.
>> It's the magnitude of
the projection
of PQ onto n,
where p is any
point on the plane,
Q is the point
off the plane,
and n is the normal
vector to the plane.
>> It simplifies it to a
nice expression like this.