Hi class.
>> Let's talk about
vector valued functions
from Section 11.1,
vector valued
functions, or functions
whose output is a vector.
Here we see some
examples of
vector valued functions in
two dimensions and
in three dimensions.
So a vector valued
function is
still a function
of a real variable t,
but its output is now
a vector and has
two components.
And the nice thing is,
is that the components
of the output
vector R functions,
we normally see
them, they are real,
real valued functions as
they are in Calculus
One and Two.
Here's a curve y
equal to x squared.
We're pretty familiar
with this one.
We want to describe
this curve with a
vector valued function.
One way to do it is to
parameterize the curve.
This is a concept
that we'll
be seeing over and over
again by parameterizing
the curve.
We have something
called a parameter.
>> T.
>> T is our new variable.
>> You can think
of it as time.
And we want to describe
the location of
the point x comma y for
any value of t.
Here we can see
that if we put
the x value and the y
value into a vector,
that gives us a
vector valued
function that
describes the curve.
>> So every value
of t gives us a
different vector.
>> And that different
vector corresponds
to the blue arrow
that you see here.
>> And notice that
the curve itself
is traced out by the
terminal point
of the arrow.
>> So what if we have
a new parameter s?
>> S is equal to two t.
>> What does that
curve look like?
>> If we were to
have the vector
valued function r of ask,
ask comma S squared.
>> The fact is it's
actually the same.
>> So this shows
that we can have
multiple parameterizations
for the same curve.
You'll notice here, if
S is equal to two t,
the rate at which a point
will move along
the curve will be
twice as fast it
with respect to t,
with respect to time,
if we're thinking
of T at time.
So that's going to do,
we're going to be
something that's
important in
later chapters is
that we can have
different parameterizations
for the same curve.
And that makes sense.
If the curve is the
path of an object,
that path can
be moving fast,
that or that object
can be moving faster,
that object can
be moving slowly.
Our curves in
two-dimensional space can be
quite exotic
and interesting
like we have here.
So this is an entire
subject unit of itself,
really is just
studying curves in
two-dimensional
space and describing
them with vector equations.
The vector equations for
this one is actually
just too complicated,
even put on the screen.
We can also describe curves
in three-dimensional space.
This way, the
only difference
is there's a
third component.
The picture that
you see here
is the curve of cosine t,
sine t comma t. And we'll
remember from calculus
that cosine t,
sine t is, are
spinning around
the unit circle.
So if you were to look
at this curve from,
from the top and
look down and
just see the x and y axis.
Any point as t,
as t moves,
the vector would
just be rotor Chang,
rooting around in a circle.
But now we have a
third component, t,
which corresponds to
the z component
of the curve.
So the parametric equations
here would be cosine t,
sine t t. So for
any value of t,
we get a yellow arrow,
and that's our vector.
And so as the t
value increases,
the vectors that we get
correspond to the
yellow vector
that you see here.
>> And its terminal
point is along
the curve with vector
valued functions.
>> Since the outputs
are vectors,
we can do all of
the things that we
did in Chapter
ten with vectors.
We can add them, we
can subtract them,
we can take their
dot products,
cross products,
all those things.
Here's a famous example
of something
called a cyclone.
So the cycle, it
is a graph that's
traced by a point rolling
along the circle.
And the question asks
us to find a vector
valued function that
models this curve.
Now this can be done
a number of ways,
but I'm going to show you
the way I thought about it.
>> Wishes to first
modeled the point just
spinning around a circle.
>> So if there's something
that's hard to do,
the best thing to
do is to think
of the easiest case.
The easiest case
that I can think
of is if you just have
a circle of radius
1 spinning around,
because we're
gonna have this
ball roll to the right.
I had the point
start down here
on the bottom angle
three pi over two.
>> And if we were just to
add our parameter t,
that just adds an angle
that would spin
around the circle,
but that would spin
around the circle
counterclockwise.
>> And we'll, we want
this to spin clockwise.
So that's why we
have minus t in
the function.
So this vector
valued function here
describes movement
around the circle
like this.
So now we just need
to do the next steps
of turning it into the
cycle that we see.
We can translate the circle
up one unit by just
adding one to the
previous function
in the y component.
And then to make
the circle move,
to make the whole
animation move to
the right is to add t
to the x component.
So for every t value,
that's just horizontally
translating
the entire circle to
the right by a value
of t. And therefore,
this is one way to
describe how to make,
how to curve, to
describe the curve
of the cycle
it with a vector
valued function.
Another important
concept, especially in
physics, is disc
displacement.
So say you have this
green curve shown here,
and we know it's described
in a vector valued
function and we know
its position at
a certain time,
times 0, and then we know
its position at
a later time,
let's say time one.
So oftentimes we want
to know where, well,
what was the change in
the position between
these two times?
And that gives us
something called
displacement,
which we can describe
with a vector
as the terminal vector
minus the initial vector,
and that tells us the
total displacement
over that time.
Finally, the fight.
Now that we have
displacement,
we can start talking about
the average change of
a vector valued function
over an interval.
This is an extension
of average value
of change from
calculus one.
When we're talking
about on average,
how much does a function
change over an interval?
Will usually you look
at the difference in
the function's
value divided
by the total
amount of time.
And it turns out
that this is exactly
the same with vector
valued functions.
Only now our functions are
vector valued
functions rather
than real valued functions.