Hi class.
>> Let's take a look at
double integration
and volume.
This is an overview
of Section 13.2.
We can define double
integrals with
Riemann sums in
a similar way
we do in calculus too,
where we sub-divide
the region of integration,
which we're going
to refer to as our.
In here we have this
circular region.
And you can see
we can estimate
the region with tiny
little rectangles.
And within each
rectangle we can find
the volume underneath
the surface of a function.
So in each rectangle we
have a width and a height,
and then the
width and length,
and then the height is
the functions value at
some point inside
the rectangle.
Now, usually in a
calculus class,
we take just any point
within that rectangle
to determine the height.
We can do in more
sophisticated
ways where maybe we take
the height to be
the maximum of
the function within
the rectangle.
But we don't really
need to worry
about that much.
But any ways for each
of these little rectangles,
we can estimate
the volume there.
And the idea is to find
these slivers of volumes
and then add them all
up to estimate
the integral.
So we can define the double
integral over a region as
the sum of all of these
sliver volume pieces,
as this part here,
which is the
magnitude of delta a,
gets close to 0.
And that's just a way
to keep track of how
big the rectangles are.
And INR book, we're
defining delta a
as the sort of
maximum length
of all the rectangles,
maximum length of
the diagonals
above rectangle.
So that small, then
all of the rectangles
are small.
And we're just
taking the sum of
these smaller and smaller
and smaller pieces.
And the limit of that is
what we're calling
the double integral.
And it's intuition is
that the volume underneath
the surface over
the region for beneath
them allows us to write
these double integrals
as iterated integrals,
so that we can
actually compute them,
but only for
certain regions.
So regions that are
bounded between
two constants with
respect to one
variable and then
between two functions
with respect to the other.
Let's take a look
at an example.
So here we have a function
x, y plus e to the y.
And we want to
find the volume,
and we're saying signed
volume because if
the graph where to go
below the xy axis,
z values will be negative
and its volume there
would count as negative.
We're trying to find
that volume under
the surface,
over the region
R, which is,
happens to be a rectangle.
In this case, the limits of
integration are quite
easy to deal with.
We have x is going between
34 and y values
going between 12.
So we can write this
integral either as a DX,
DY integral where we hold y
constant between
12 and then
integrate with respect to
X from three to four,
or vice versa, where
we hold x constant
between 34 and
then integrate
Y from one to two.
And either way,
if we compute
these inter
iterated integrals
will get the same value.
The properties of
double integrals
are very familiar.
Thankfully, they're
pretty much the same as
integrals over a
region in calculus,
to a one-dimensional
region,
we can pull constants out,
add, and subtract them.
If the function
is positive,
then the integral
should be positive.
If you have two functions,
one is always greater than
the other that
moves like the
integral of the
larger one to be
greater than the integral
of the smaller one.
And number five is the part
that might not seem that
important at first,
but incredibly important,
which says that
if we're trying
to find the
volume underneath
the surface of a function
over a particular region.
And maybe it's that reasons
complicated or has
a couple parts.
And it's difficult to write
a singular
iterated integral,
integral that will do that.
>> We can cut our into
pieces that are
non-overlapping,
in whose union
is the whole,
the whole space R.
>> And then we
can just find
those individual integrals
and add them up.
So here's a double integral
of the function
form minus y.
And we're trying
to find the volume
of this between the
two parabolas here.
>> So the first thing
we always do is sketch
the region of
integration just to
get a visual of where
we are finding integral.
And here we have
our two functions.
>> And we have the
choice to evaluate the
integral as an iterated
integral with dx,
dy, or dy dx.
Whatever happens to be
easier is usually
the best choice.
Here I'm choosing
to do dy, dx, dy y.
Because if we add
up for any fixed
y from 0 to four,
we can integrate from x
is going from
left to right.
And left to right
means x goes
from y squared
over four here,
22 square root of y.
So the way I'm setting
up this problem here,
and you can set up
easily with edX as well.
But I'm setting up as
an integral dx, d y.
And then the limits
of integration
are determined
by the sketch
of the region here.
Then we just calculate
the integral using
an iterative process
where we hold y
constant and then integrate
the inside as if
y is a constant
with respect to x.
And that means finding
an antiderivative and
using the fundamental
theorem of calculus,
then we can expand
everything out.
And now we just have
a normal polynomial
with respect to
one variable y.
And we would integrate
that in the usual way.
Sometimes were
actually forced
to change the limits
of integration.
Consider this
integral here,
e to the negative
x squared dx d y.
This is a famous example
because let's say we
try to evaluate
this integral just
the way that it is.
Well, that would
mean trying to find
an anti-derivative
of the function e to
the negative x squared
with respect to x.
And this is a
famous example from
calculus to this is
a Gaussian function.
It does not have
an antiderivative
and elementary
antiderivative.
So that's an actual
impossible task.
If we were to
try to evaluate
this integral as
it's written,
we could not use the
fundamental theorem
of calculus.
We would have to use
some numerical
approximation or
something like
that instead.
Well, we can do is
investigate the region of
integration and
see if we can now
rewrite the integral
in terms of dy,
dx and then perhaps
give us a function that
does have an
antiderivative.
So if we sketch
the region of
integration here,
we see that y between 03,
we're going to integrate
x from y to three.
What we'd like
to do is rewrite
the integral and change
the order of integration.
So now we can see for
every x between 03,
y is indeed going to be
integrated from 0 to x.
And we see that reflected
in the integral right here.
Now, the very first move we
make is the iterated
integral on the inside,
which is the find the
anti-derivative
with respect to y.
Well, e to the
negative x squared
is a constant with
respect to y.
So you just attach a
why to it and then
apply the fundamental
theorem of
calculus at the endpoints.
And the result
is a function
that now when we
find the antiderivative
with respect to x,
we can do it using
substitution.
We can use the notion of
double integrals to find
the average value
of a function
over a region is a
function of two variables.
And here we're just
using the idea that
a function's average
on a region is
the volume underneath
that surface
over the region divided
by the area of the base.
That's an easy way to
remember this formula.