Let's take a look at
the divergence theorem for
higher dimensions
and Stokes theorem
in our final section 14.7,
we previously did
previously studied
the divergence theorem over
a two-dimensional region.
So we were able
to calculate
the total flux
across a boundary,
call a closed curve c,
by integrating the
divergence on the inside.
Now we have a
surface and we want
to calculate
the total flux
through the surface.
Again, we'll do
that by integrating
the three-dimensional
region of
the divergence
of the inside.
Let's take a look
at an example.
Here we have a region D
and is bounded by
plane z equal to 0,
is equal to 2x,
the cylinder
x equal one
minus y squared.
And we have a vector field
f that surrounds it.
We could find the
total flux across
the surfaces by
parameterizing
each surface and then
calculating those
surface integrals with
the normal vector
and C accumulate
the total amount that's
gone through the surface.
Instead, we can setup
with the spine the
divergence of the
vector field,
which is a relatively
easy calculation.
And then integrate that
divergence function
on the inside,
which is a relatively
straightforward
triple integral.
So we see that
the total flux
across the surface
here is 16 over five.
And we didn't have to do
any parameterizations of
the service Stokes theorem
is a generalization
of Green's theorem.
Now we have a
surface S and we
can find the line
integral by adding up
the curl on the inside
of the surface with
the service integral.
So here we have
a function that describes
a plane seven
minus 2x minus 2y,
and then a curve that
sits on that plane,
which is a circle
of radius one.
What we can do is
first parameterize
the curve C. Well,
first we'll parameterize
actually the unit disk,
which is cosine U, sine U,
by adding one to
the x component
and y component,
that shifts the circle
here to the first quadrant.
And then we want to
describe the whole disk.
And so by
multiplying times V,
V plays the role of the
radius of the disc.
So it's a shift of
a polar coordinate
description
of the unit disk.
Now the first
two coordinates
here of our
parameterization,
or the X value
and the y value
of this unit disc
sitting in the
first quadrant.
Now we use that x value
and that y value,
put them into
the function to
find the corresponding
z value.
So that's where the,
that's how this
parameterization was found.
You use parameter
goes between
02 pi and these primary
goes between 01.
We can calculate the curl
of the vector field
that we're given,
which is just these partial
derivatives taken
the differences.
And that allows us to
calculate the
surface integral.
So the surface integral
is the integral
of the curl,
which we found previously,
dot product with
the cross product
of the partial derivatives
of our parameterization.
And this is a fairly
straightforward integral.
And we get that the,
the total is three pi