Let's take a look at unit,
tangent and normal vectors.
This is an overview
of Section 11.4 in
a book or call
it the velocity vector is
the derivative of
the position vector.
The unit tangent vector is
the velocity vector
divided by its magnitude,
which scales it to
have length. One.
>> Picture here we see
a curve and we see
a couple instances of
the velocity vector
scaled by length one.
>> So what you
see in red is
the unit tangent vectors
at those points.
Similarly, since
the unit tangent
vector is constant,
we learned earlier that the
derivative of a constant
vector valued function
is always orthogonal to
the function itself.
And that's the case
here. If we take
the unit tangent vector
and take its derivative,
that gives us a
vector orthogonal to
the tangent vector called
the normal vector.
And then we scale it
by its length to get
the unit normal vector
unit means one.
So now we have two
vectors of length one.
We have the
tangent vector and
we have
the normal vector which
is perpendicular.
>> Let's take a
look at an example.
This is the simple helix
that we've looked at
in previous videos.
>> Find the unit tangent
vector at pi over
two and the unit
normal vector
at pi over two.
And graph the
initial points where
the vectors are sitting
at the position
pi over two.
To find the unit
tangent vector,
we just need to
take our vector
valued function r position,
take its derivative, find
its magnitude with
the distance formula.
And then the unit
tangent vector is
just the velocity divided
by its magnitude.
And that comes together
as this vector here.
Now add pi over two.
We just simply put
pi over two in for
value of t and simplify.
And we end up getting
the vector negative
one over root two comma 0,
comma one over root two.
This is supposed to
have length one,
so it's good to
check our answers.
You can take
the square root
of each component
squared and you
can check that
we actually do
get one there.
To find the unit
normal vector,
we need to take
the derivative
of the unit tangent vector.
>> So we found
that, we found
a unit tangent
vector above.
>> We take the derivative
of each component,
and these are just
derivatives of
sines and cosines.
And we get a new vector.
We can calculate that
derivative at pi over two.
>> We can take
its magnitude and
that gives us
the unit normal vector
at pi over two.
>> But here is
0 negative 10.
>> So if we have the
position vector,
which we originally
had was cosine t,
sine t t in our
animation here,
that's the vector that's in
yellow and that's
the helix vector.
>> So that vector
is going to
indicate climbing up
the helix as t increases.
Then for each value of t,
we have the vector
valued function for
the unit tangent
vector in blue.
And we have the vector
valued function
for the unit normal
vector that is in red.
>> If we're
thinking about this
as position
or movement in
three-dimensional space.
>> We have the position,
we have the velocity blue,
and we have the
acceleration red.
>> Notice that the blue and
the red are scaled
to have length
one in two-dimensional
space.
>> Finding the
normal vectors are
especially nice and easy.
And if you have
the unit tangent,
if you have the unit
tangent vector,
then the normal vector
is orthogonal to it.
And do remember that
if you have the
slope of a line,
the slope that's
perpendicular
to that is the
negative reciprocal.
>> Well, that's,
that's similar here.
>> If they couldn't
components of
the unit tangent
vector t1, t2,
you just simply flip
them and take the
negative of one of them and
then you get the
unit normal vector.
>> We can write
the acceleration
into components that are
orthogonal this way.
>> So as our projectile
moves in space,
you have the unit
tangent vector
and you have the
unit normal vector.
And we can decompose
the acceleration
into these two parts
and add them together.
This is useful
because the number
that's in front of the
unit tangent vector.
So it tells us how much of
the acceleration
contributes to the speed.
And the number in front of
the unit normal
vector tells us
how much is
contributing
perpendicular to travel.