Let's take a look at
the multivariable
chain rule.
>> In section 12.51,
we want to revisit
some things we know
about the chain rule
from calculus one.
>> If we have a
single variable
function y equals g of x,
that gives us the
mileage of the vehicle,
meaning y gives
us Miles and
x is the gallons
of gasoline.
>> And then we also have
x being a function of t,
which in this
case is dollar.
>> So this is a situation
where Y is described as
a composition of
functions g with
f. If we want to
know how is the
function wise mileage
changing with respect
to the dollar?
Then we can use
the chain rule.
The rate at which the
miles is changing
with respect
dollar is equal to
the rate at which
the miles is
changing with respect
to gallons of
gasoline times
that the ray which
is changing with respect
to gasoline with dollars.
>> And the chain rule for
one variable is usually
written like this.
Now the Chain Rule for, for
multivariable functions,
we can think of
the surface of
our graph of a function
of two variables.
>> And we want to know
how is that function
changing if we have,
if we're traveling
along that surface as,
let's say, a function
of time t in this case.
So in this example, we have
a circle in the domain,
and we can be
travelling around
that circle as a
function of time
of x and t comma y of
t. But that it
tells us how fast we're
spinning around the circle.
>> We need to use
the information from
the terrain of
the function,
or we going up or down
to tell us how fast it's
moving up or down on
the surface of
the graph itself.
>> So this is motivation
for the multi-variable
chain rule,
which says that the rate at
which the elevation
is changing with
respect to time has to
do with the rate at
which you're changing with
respect to x and y axis,
your speed or your velocity
and the terrain itself,
which is what the
partial derivative
tells us.
>> So this is the
multivariable chain rule.
>> It's often
remembered with
this convenient
diagram here.
>> The derivative
with respect to,
derivative of z
with respect to t.
>> As you go along
the branches and
multiply and then you
add up the result in
the corresponding,
add up the
corresponding branches.
>> Here we have an
object traveling
along a path with some
given information.
>> We know the
partial derivatives,
we know how z is
changing with
respect to x and y.
And then we also
know how x and
y are changing
with respect to t.
>> Again, the partial z,
partial x is information
about how steep
the graph is,
those places and dx,
d t, and d t.
>> So tell us
how fast we're
moving in the x
and y directions
respectively.
>> So this is
just a straightforward
application
of the multi-variable
chain rule,
and it illustrates the
connection between the,
the terrain and the speed.
>> We can also
have functions
of more than one parameter,
S and T. And if you want
to find how z is changing
with respect to S,
you can often
remember it with
a tree diagram like here.
If we want to find
housing is changing as we
go along the branches
with the S and
multiply and then add
up those branches.
>> And then similarly
with respect to t,
there's a nice
side effect with
the multivariable
chain rule that helps
us find implicit
derivatives.
>> So let's look at
the case where we have
a function of a couple
of areas equal to 0.
>> And then what
we're gonna do is
set acts as just a
function of itself,
acts as a function of x.
>> So we can write
out the chain rule.
But in this case,
the derivative of
z with respect to x and
z is a constant function 0,
we just get 0 and dx,
dx is just one.
So if we put these
two parts here,
we get that the DY,
DX is just equal
to negative
of the derivative
after select Ax
divided by I drove f
with respect to y.
>> So neat shortcut formula
for finding DY, DX.
>> Let's look
at an example.
>> So given the
implicitly defined
function here,
find Y prime,
which is d by dx.
>> The first step is to,
we want to use the
assumptions of
the implicit
differentiation formula.
So if we put everything
on one side,
we now have a
function that's
equal to 0 or equal
to a constant,
we can take the
partial derivatives of
that function with
respect to x,
with respect to y.
>> And just apply
the formula
that dy dx is equal to the
negative of f partial x
divided by f partial y.